<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The seaven golden candlestickes Englands honour. The great mysterie of Gods mercie yet to come. With peace to the pure in heart aduising to vnitie among our selues. By Richard Bernard, minister at Batcombe in Somersetshire.</title>
            <author>Bernard, Richard, 1568-1641.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 130 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09320</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1963</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113795</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849025</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849025</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14154</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09320)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14154)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 699:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The seaven golden candlestickes Englands honour. The great mysterie of Gods mercie yet to come. With peace to the pure in heart aduising to vnitie among our selues. By Richard Bernard, minister at Batcombe in Somersetshire.</title>
                  <author>Bernard, Richard, 1568-1641.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[96] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by William Stansby] for Iohn Badge, dwelling in Pauls Church-yard at the signe of the Greene Dragon,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Miscellaneous treatises, each with caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B-H I⁴ (-A1,I4, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Church History --  17th Century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14154:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14154:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SEAVEN GOLDEN CAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DLESTICKES. <hi>Englands Honour.</hi> THE GREAT MY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STERIE OF GODS MERCIE YET TO COME. <hi>WITH</hi> Peace to the pure in heart aduiſing to VNITIE among our ſelues. <hi>By</hi> RICHARD BERNARD, <hi>Miniſter at</hi> Batcombe <hi>in</hi> Somerſetſhire.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Iohn Budge,</hi> dwelling in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard at the ſigne of the Greene Dragon. 1621.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14154:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14154:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE, <hi>WILLIAM</hi> Lord <hi>CAVENDISH</hi> Earle of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uonſhire;</hi> IOHN <hi>Lord</hi> DARCY, <hi>Baron of Meinell;</hi> IOHN <hi>Lord</hi> HOLLEYS Baron of <hi>Houghton,</hi> his very honourable good Lords, heere increaſe of all true <hi>honour, and hereafter the fruition of</hi> that happines which is in Heauen. AND TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL
<list>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Robert Philips,</hi> AND Sir <hi>Iohn Horner,</hi> KNIGHTS.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Powlet,</hi> AND <hi>Robert Hopton.</hi> ESQVIRES.</item>
               </list> Iuſtices of the Peace in the Countie of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> louers of their Countrie, my <hi>worthily honoured good Friends, loue and</hi> peace be multiplyed, internally within themſelues, externally to one an other, with hope of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall comfort in the end.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HO:) (RIGHT WOR:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our ready condeſcending at my requeſt to grace my Perſon with your
<pb facs="tcp:14154:3"/> ioynt teſtimonie together, maketh me now thus bold to craue your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and acceptance together to countenance this my labour.</p>
            <p>That which here I offer to your view is firſt the face of <hi>the ſeuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold eſtate of Chriſts Church,</hi> typed out in the ſeuen Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> vnder the title of <hi>the ſeuen golden Candleſtickes.</hi> In this you may behold what is alreadie paſt, what things are now in preſent being (in which the Papiſts make themſelues merrie; but it is their <hi>Cygnea cantio,</hi> before their day of mourning) and what the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate hereafter ſhall be, which wee are to exſpect and looke for in the appointed time. In the ſecond place, is added <hi>Englands Honour,</hi> wherein is ſhewed how highly, and that many wayes God hath aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced this noble Nation, to incourage
<pb facs="tcp:14154:3"/> vs ſtill in his ſeruice againſt that Antichriſtion power, and Heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Superstition. In the third place, is prooued that <hi>great My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie</hi> of the ſaluation of that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient people of God, much hindered by that Romiſh Religion. In conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, is an aduice to Peace and Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie at home, that wee may bend our ſtrength againſt our Enemies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad.</p>
            <p>I humbly craue pardon, if here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I haue bin ouer-bold to preſent your Honours, and other ſo worthy Perſonages, with ſuch ſmall Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes. I know them little in ſhew, but not ſo in ſubſtance. The Church is the Spouſe of Chriſt, the verie Queene of Heauen, heere ſhee is liuely painted out. The glory of our Kingdome is our Crowne, and peace with loue the bond of perfection; the taſte of theſe things, I hope,
<pb facs="tcp:14154:4"/> ſhall not bee vnacceptable, neyther the good will of him that offereth the ſame, for no other end verily, but to leaue a teſtimonie to the World of his humble ſeruice, and of his duty in all thankfulneſſe, who doth and euer will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge himſelfe,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Batcombe, <date>March. 10.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Honours and Worſhips much bounden and to be commanded, RICHARD BERNARD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:14154:4"/>
            <head>THE SEAVEN GOLDEN CAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DLESTICKES <hi>OR</hi> THE SEAVEN FOLD Eſtate of Gods Church here vpon <hi>Earth, typed out in the ſeauen</hi> Churches of ASIA.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not a conceit, but an opinion more then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that the ſeuen Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> are Types of the whole Church militant; which opinion, though it be in a ſort onely barely deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered of ſome, and by ſome others ſo ſet out, as thereby many take occaſion
<pb facs="tcp:14154:5"/> to reiect it, but more out of a ſiniſter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, then of any ſollid ground; yet if they pleaſe to weigh the reaſons, and to conſider well how theſe and the times doe anſwere one another, they will more eaſily yeeld vnto the Truth.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Is it not plainly ſaid, in the end of the whole Propheſie, that Ieſus Chriſt ſent his Angell to teſtifie theſe things vnto vs <hi>in the Churches,</hi> to wit, in thoſe ſeuen Churches of <hi>Aſia?</hi> for no other are mentioned in the whole Propheſie; ſo as whatſoeuer in the Reuelation was after deliuered, the ſame was repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted generally in the fore-ſaid Churches before.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The number of ſeuen, as in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places of this Propheſie, repeated thirtie ſeuen times, is a number of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; and is put for all of that, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the number is giuen, as the ſeuen Starres for all the Angels of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; the ſeuen ſpirits for the ſeuen-fold Graces thereof; ſo the ſeuen Churches, for all the Chriſtian Churches, or rather the ſeuen-fold eſtate of one and the ſame Church of Chriſt. And ſeeing there were
<pb facs="tcp:14154:5"/> more Churches in thoſe parts, we may well thinke that the number of ſeuen was taken for further purpoſe, then to note out only the preſent eſtate of thoſe ſeuen Churches, to which <hi>Iohn</hi> wrote.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Iohn</hi> in the end of euery Epiſtle, makes a generall exhortation, ſaying, He that hath an eare, let him heare, what the Spirit ſaith, <hi>vnto the Churches:</hi> yet in the beginning of euery Epiſtle, is hee co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded onely to write particularly to the Angell thereof, and of ſuch things as touched him, and the eſtate of his Church. Therfore when <hi>Iohn</hi> concludeth ſo with an exhortation <hi>to all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> what elſe doth hee but thereby teach all thoſe Churches, whereof that particular Church is a Type, or, if you will, ſo by one, all the ſeuen, and by them all Chriſtian Churches?</p>
            <p n="4">4. In the Epiſtles there bee many things which muſt neceſſarily perſwade to a farther extent, then onely to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent eſtate of euery of thoſe particular Churches; as firſt the <hi>maruellous order,</hi> according to the courſe and eſtate of Chriſts Church, both in the gifts, and
<pb facs="tcp:14154:6"/> graces with decay of them, as alſo in <hi>the creeping vp of Antichriſt,</hi> and the Churches recouery and growing into a better eſtate euen to the end, as ſhall bee ſhewed in paralleling of theſe Churches and the eſtate of Chriſts Church from time to time. Then ſome things ſpoken of the particular Churches, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſible bee taken as onely meant of them. As of the ten dayes tribulation, which Expoſitours interpret of a perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution longer, then can agree by Storie to haue falne vpon <hi>Smyrna</hi> in <hi>Iohns</hi> time, or after. Likewiſe the great honour, which is promiſed to the Angell of the Church of <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> that the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Iewes in <hi>Smyrna Reuel.</hi> 2. 9. ſhould fall downe to him, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 3. 9. and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance from the tryall which ſhould come vpon all the World, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 3. 10. cannot bee vnderſtood ſimply of that Angell. Wee finde not in any Hiſtorie ſuch renowne to that Angell, neither of ſuch perill, and gracious deliuerance; but theſe things are ſpoken with reſpect to the Churches eſtate, as this ſhould be a Type thereof. Againe, who can reade
<pb facs="tcp:14154:6"/> the tearmes vſed, and the perſons na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, as <hi>Iewes, Synagogue, Balaam,</hi> and <hi>Ieſabell,</hi> with the degrees and procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings thereof: but thereby will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued ſome other thing intended in thoſe Churches? It is maruelous to ſee how the degrees of euill are ſet out, in the foure firſt Churches; in <hi>Epheſus</hi> are <hi>Sathans Seeds-men,</hi> falſe Apoſtles; in <hi>Smyrna Sathans Synagogue;</hi> in <hi>Pergamus Sathans Throne;</hi> in <hi>Thiatyra the</hi> very <hi>Iezabel</hi> and <hi>Depths of Sathan.</hi> In the three laſt, no menton of any of theſe, becauſe they doe ſet out the Church de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from Sathans Seedes-men, from his Aſſemblies, from his Throne, and from the <hi>Ieſabel</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Depths of Sathan therein, and doe ſhew the threefold eſtate of the Church come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> as in <hi>Sardis</hi> a weake refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, in <hi>Philadelphia</hi> an excellent dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of the Church, and then afterwards the <hi>Laodicean</hi> condition. Who ſo mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth theſe, how can he deeme otherwiſe of theſe Churches, then of the Types of Chriſts Church?</p>
            <p n="5">5. Wee may bee mooued further ſo
<pb facs="tcp:14154:7"/> to thinke from the ſituation of theſe Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and from the order which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet obſerueth in writing vnto them, from <hi>Epheſus</hi> Northward to <hi>Smyrna,</hi> &amp; yet more North to <hi>Pergamus,</hi> from this to <hi>Thyatira</hi> Eaſtward, and ſo more and more to <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> and then bendeth Southward to <hi>Laodicea.</hi> Which ſituati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on pointeth vs out the declining of the Church to darkneſſe, and then a recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring by little and little light againe, ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Eaſt &amp; Southeaſt, from the North. The Church came from <hi>Iudea</hi> out of the Eaſt, it went a little Southward, but far Weſt, then into theſe Northerne parts, and ſo Northeaſt, and ſhall circle about till it come to be a Church againe in <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea,</hi> at the Conuerſion of the <hi>Iewes;</hi> when the fulneſſe of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſhall come in.</p>
            <p n="6">6. And laſtly, the anſwerableneſſe of the Type and Antitype will fully giue ſatisfaction in this point, which that it may appeare, I will will here parallell them together.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:14154:7"/>
               <head>THE FIRST GOLDEN <hi>CANDLESTICK.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>THE FIRST CHVRCH.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>In the Type.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">In the Antitype.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">The Church of Epheſus.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>The Primitiue Church and Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſine State.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1. <hi>THis is the first, &amp; as it were chiefe of the other, ſet in the firſt place.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1. THis is the firſt Church, and therefore called the Primitiue Church, hauing place and prerogatiue aboue the reſt.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2. <hi>This was pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Saint</hi> Paul <hi>the Apoſtle,</hi> Acts 19. <hi>and 20. and gathered of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Beleeuers fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amonge notorious Heathen Idolaters and wicked men,</hi> Acts 19. 28. Eph. 2. 12. <hi>and here</hi> Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy <hi>was placed to order all things for Doctrine and Diſcipline,</hi> 1. Tim. 1. 3.</cell>
                        <cell>2. This was planted by the Apoſtles, and gathered of <hi>Iewes</hi> and Heathen Idolaters, <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> they being commanded by Chriſt to goe into all the World, to preach the Goſpell, and when they had planted Churches, they did appoint <hi>Timothyes,</hi> that is, Biſhops and Elders for Doctrine &amp; Diſcipline for wel ordering of the Churches. <hi>Mat. 28. Acts 2. &amp; 3. &amp; 8. &amp; 10. 11. &amp;c. Acts 14. 23.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:8"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3. <hi>This was plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with much affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the Apoſtle and Brethren.</hi> 1. Cor. 15. 32. <hi>and there were many Aduerſaries,</hi> 1. Cor. 16. 9.</cell>
                        <cell>3. This was planted with great and manifolde perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; The Apoſtles were mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyred, and the Chriſtian Paſtors and people put to death euery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where; for the Goſpell of Chriſt had a World of Aduerſaries, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Reigne of the Heathen Emperours of <hi>Rome. Acts 7. 23. Euſeb. l. 2, c. 25. l. 3, c. 15. 29. l. 4. c. 15. Oroſ. l. c. 7. 10. Niceph. l. 2.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4. <hi>This hath Chriſt ſet out vnto it, as hauing ſeuen ſtarres in his right hand, and walking in the midſt of the ſeuen golden Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſtickes.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>4. This had Chriſt protecting his faithfull Paſtors with the power of his right hand, and ſhewed himſelfe in it, in an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary manner by his holy Spirit, effectually working by his Word, and making it renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Miracles and Wonders, <hi>Acts 2. &amp; 3. &amp; 5. &amp; 8. 17. &amp; 14. 10. Rom. 15. 19. Iornand. de temp. &amp; Succeſſ. l. 1. in Reg Rom. ſerie. Theod l. 1. 7. Sleid. de 4. Imp. l. 2. Aug. de Ciuit. Dei, l. 8. c. 15.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5. <hi>The Angell of this Church was</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>5. The Angels of this Church, firſt, the Apoſtles, then the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicall</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:8"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>at the beginning and ſo continued for a ſpace full of vertue, very labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, patiently ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering and fainted not.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>men, and others after them, which were aduanced to authoritie, not by money, but by good report, were full of vertue, painfull Preachers, and many made Expoſitions &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries vpon the Scriptures, and others publiſhed Apologies and their defence of Chriſtian Religion, and patiently ſuffered for the Truth, as did <hi>Pollycar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus, Iuſt. Martyr. Germanicus</hi> and infinite others. <hi>Tertull. Apolog. c. 39. Iuſt. Apol. 2. Trithemius de Scriptor. Ecclis. Quadratus. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtides. Iust. Martyr. Melito Biſhop of Sardis and others. Euſeb. l. 3. c. 32. l. 4. &amp; 8. 3.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6. <hi>This Church was troubled with falſe Apoſtles and wicked Nicholai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans: but the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell was zealous, could not beare with them, but v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed boldly his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <p>6. So the Primitiue Church was troubled with many falſe Apoſtles, Heretikes and wicked liuers, and Antichriſts, but the Angels were then zealous and could not beare with them but</p>
                           <p>1. They fled their familiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie (as <hi>Iohn</hi> did out of the Bath from <hi>Cerinthus) Titus 3.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:9"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>his hatred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their wicked neſſe.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <p>2. They communicated not in words (as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> ſaith, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Euſeb.</hi>) ſo zealous they were, as <hi>Polycarpus</hi> his anſwere to <hi>Marcion</hi> ſheweth.</p>
                           <p>3. Some wept and lamented that they had receiued Baptiſme of Heretickes.</p>
                           <p>4. Some confuted them, as <hi>Agrippa Caſtor</hi> did <hi>Baſilides,</hi> and <hi>Iuſt. Martyr</hi> did <hi>Marcion.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>5. They kept the wicked from the Sacraments, from Prayer, and beeing found ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate, cutthem off from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Church, as they had learned by Apoſtolicall precept and practiſe, 1. <hi>Cor. 5. 1. Tim. 1. 20. 2. Cor. 11. 12. Euſeb. l. 4. Aug. l. de hereſ. Epiph. de hereſ. Iren. l. 1. &amp; 3. Euſeb. l. 4. 14. 2. Iohn ver. 7. 1. Iohn 2. 18. 22. &amp; 4. 3. Euſeb. l. 7. c. 8. Euſeb. l. 4. c. 7. Trithem. de Scriptor. Ecclis. Iuſt. Mart. Apol. l. 2. Tertul. Apologet. c. 2. Origen. on Matth. tract. 35. &amp; 7. hom. on Ioſ. Socrat. l. 1. c. 17. Cyprian Epiſt. ad Cler. Rom.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:9"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7. <hi>This Angel towardes the end, forſooke his firſt Loue, ſo as this Church did lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh and grow re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe in Religious duties, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore euils could not but grow vp there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>7. So this glorious Church, loſt of herloue and zeale, her An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels became more remiſſe in their duties, neglecting Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, and ſaith <hi>Euſeb.</hi> through much eaſe, libertie, &amp; ſecuritie, they degenerated from the true rule of Pietie. Biſhops againſt Biſhops, people one againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yea, hypocriſie and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice ſo raged, ſaith he, that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution beeing begunne on o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, they had no ſenſe nor feeling thereof. <hi>Cyprian. Epiſt. l. 4 Ambroſe on 1. Tim. 1. Euſeb. l. 8. c. 1. Fox Acts &amp; Monuments, p. 69.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8. <hi>This is threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, for the decay of loue, to haue the Candleſtick remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued out of his place</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>8. So this Church, for the decay of loue, and increaſe of euill, felt ſo the LORDS wrath, as if indeed, the LORD had pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to haue had his Church no more vpon Earth. For hee ſendeth vpon them that raging Tyrant <hi>Diocleſian</hi> with his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion <hi>Maximinianus,</hi> to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thouſands, to burne the Scriptures, and to raze downe</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:10"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>Churches from the very foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of them. <hi>Euſebius lib. 8: cap. 2. 3.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <q>Though the Lord doth here threaten, yet hee promiſeth a reward of happineſſe.</q>
               <q>He then that hath an eare, let him heare what the Spirit ſaith vnto the Churches.</q>
               <p>Thus much for the ſtate of the Primitiue Church, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the dayes of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, liuely ſet out in this Church of <hi>Epheſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14154:10"/>
                  <head>CONSIDERATIONS FOR INSTRVCTION <hi>AND VSE.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>WHerein wee may obſerue theſe things. Firſt, Where God ſo w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Seed of his Word by his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, there Sathan would thirſt in his falſe Apoſtle to ſow Tares. Secondly, That in thoſe Primitiue Times there were excellent Angels, full of good workes, patient and laborious. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That the faithfull Angels could not endure or beare with thoſe which were euill, ſo zealous were they for the Lord and his Truth. Fourthly, That Sathans inſtruments will aſſume to themſelues faire Names and Titles. Fiftly, That therefore the Church will try and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine them, and ſo either admit them or reiect them, as ſhee ſhall finde cauſe. Sixtly, That excellent men may decay in their firſt Loue. Seuenthly, that euen the decay of loue may cauſe God to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooue his Candleſticke, except men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:14154:11"/>
               <head>THE SECOND GOLDEN <hi>CANDLESTICK,</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>THE SECOND CHVRCH.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>In the Type.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">In the Antitype.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">The Church of Smyrna.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>The Smyrnean ſtate of Christs Church.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1. <hi>THIS was the next to Epheſus North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; and ſo in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree worſe, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the wicked in it. For Sathan in Epheſus had but his ſeeds-men, falſe Apoſtles, but heere the Deuill hath a Synagogue.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1. THIS was the next to the Primitiue Church, from <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, to <hi>Gratian</hi> the Emperour, <hi>Anno</hi> 383. The Primitiue Church was troubled with Seeds-men of Sathan, but here within this ſpace were Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies and Synods of Deuil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Heretickes. <hi>Socrat. Scholast. l. 2. c 5. Hiſtor. Tripart. l. 2. cap. 10. Funct. Chronol. Sozem. l. 3. c. 11.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2. <hi>The LORD ſetteth out himſelf, firſt in his Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, in more hidden termes, and then in his humanity plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>2. For that, at this time his Diuinitie was queſtioned, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed of many, but no doubt made of his Humanitie: though one <hi>Apollinaris</hi> held the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie and Diuinitie one Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:11"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>&amp; <hi>both diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Socrat. Schol. l. 1. Hiſt. Trip. l. 9. c. 3. Baſil. Epiſt. 74. Aug. l. de Haereſ.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3. <hi>The Angell of this Church was laborious, greatly afflicted, and poore.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>3. There were at this time painfull Paſtors, but much afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the fury of the <hi>Arians,</hi> as may bee ſeene in that one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Arius</hi> &amp; his Aſſociates, alſo in <hi>Macarius, Marcellus, Paulus,</hi> and other Biſhops companions with them in the Truth and in affliction, <hi>Euſtathius</hi> with many Prieſts and Deacons ſent into ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. <hi>Ruff. l. 1. Ruff. l. 2. c. 7. Hieron. in Catal. Ammianus l. 15. Baſil. de Trinit. Socrat. li. 1. c. 20. 21. &amp; l. 2. c. 7. 8. 10. 12. &amp; 4. 13. 14 17. Athan. Apol. 2. Athan. Epist. ad vitam ſolitariam agentes.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4. <hi>But this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell was rich to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>4. So theſe men were endued with great graces, as appeared by their Learning, Zeale and holy Conſtancie, ſo as (taking <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius</hi> the Standard-bearer for an inſtance) they became ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable and were highly eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:12"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>of, &amp; wanted not entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Socrat. Scho. l. 2. &amp; 18. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. in Chronol.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5. <hi>This Angell was blaſphemed by counterfeit Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, calling the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues Iewes, and were not, but the Synagogue of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>5. So theſe Angels were not abuſed by Heathen Tyrants, as formerly, but by hereticall Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, <hi>Arian</hi> Biſhops, counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiting ſometime to bee of the Orthodox Verity, but were dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable inſtruments of Sathan; of whoſe blaſphemies and ſlanders againſt the true Paſtors, and eſpecially againſt <hi>Athanaſius, Euſtathius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch, Macarius</hi> and others, wee may reade in diuers Authors. <hi>Socrat. Scho. l. 1. c. 10. 18. 25. Hist. Magd. cent. 4. c. 9. Socrat. l. 1. c. 20. 21. 23. Atha. Apol. 2. Theod. l. 1. c. 26. &amp; l. 2. c. 8. 9. 10. Sozom. l. 2. c. 25. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. in Catal. Atha. in Epiſt. ad vitam ſolitariam agentes.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6. <hi>This Angel is encouraged, and willed net to feare.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>6. So the Lord encouraged and rayſed vp godly men of an vndaunted Spirit, not fearing troubles to maintayne the truth, as <hi>Atha. Alexander</hi> of <hi>Constan.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:12"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Oſius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Corduba, Paph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutius, Spiridion, Baſil,</hi> and many others cited by <hi>Lu. Oſiand.</hi> in thoſe troubleſome times vnder <hi>Arian</hi> Emperours, and among furiouſly raging Heretickes. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crat. l. 1. c. 5. 18. 25. l. 4. 21. Niceph. Atha. in Epiſt. ad ſolitariam vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam agentes. Hiſtor. Magd. cent. 4. Ruffi. l. 1. c. 4. Theod. l. 1. c. 7. in Epit. cent. l. 1. c. 3. cent. 4.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7. <hi>This Angel was foretold of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, and perſecution by the Deuill, but yet the perſecution ſhould not continue long.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>7. This came to paſſe vnder <hi>Conſtance</hi> and <hi>Valens,</hi> the <hi>Arian</hi> Emperours led by Satan, to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe and to permit to bee practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all crueltie againſt the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxe Fathers, and true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Beleeuers: of which wee may reade at large in diuers Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors. But the Lord ſuffered not long this cruell perſecution, nor the Perſecutors to reign long, for this cruel <hi>Valens</hi> reigned but 13. years, <hi>An. 381. Atha. in Ep. advit. ſolit. agentes. &amp; in Apol. ad Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtan. Sozom. l. 3. 4. 6. Theo. l. 2. &amp; 4. Socrat. l. 2. 38. &amp; 4. 2. 6. 13. 14. 16.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:13"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>17. 19. <hi>Greg. Nazi. Orat. ad Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cop. &amp; ad Arian. &amp; in laudem Baſil. &amp; Hieron. Socrat. l. 4. c. 13.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8. <hi>This Angell was exhorted to bee faithfull to the death, and was promiſed to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded with a Crowne of Life.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>8. So there were many moſt valiant, and faithfully conſtant to the death, as is before ſhewed in <hi>Athanaſius</hi> and others, and heere I cannot but mention <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil,</hi> and his moſt vndaunted Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit before the <hi>Arian</hi> Preſident of <hi>Antioch, Valens</hi> the Emperour beeing there preſent, by which holy and faithful reſolution they haue gotten heere the Crowne of Prayſe, and in Heauen the Crowne of Glory. <hi>Socrat. li. 4. c. 21. Sozom. l. 6. 16. Theod. l. 4. c. 19.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <q>Hee that hath an eare, let him heare what the Spirit faith to the Churches.</q>
               <q>
                  <hi>He that ouercommeth ſhall not be hurt of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond death.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>Thus much of the ſtate of Chriſts Church from <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> to <hi>Gratian,</hi> ſet out in this Church of <hi>Smyrna.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14154:13"/>
                  <head>CONSIDERATIONS FOR INSTRVCTION <hi>AND VSE.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FIrſt, that when the Church decayeth, Sathans Kingdome increaſeth: In the former Church were onely. Seeds<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of Sathan, but the Church decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in loue, here Sathan hath his Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue. Secondly, the troubleſome e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of his Church is well knowne to Chriſt. Thirdly, That ſuch as be vnder affliction and poore in outward eſtate, may yet bee inwardly rich before God. Fourthly, that very Enemies and Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers of God and his people, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Synagogue of Sathan would yet bee held and taken for true Worſhippers of God. Fiftly, that God permits ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time the Deuill and his Inſtruments to vexe his people; but yet both the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and time is ſet downe by the LORD: And therefore no cauſe to feare.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:14154:14"/>
               <head>THE THIRD GOLDEN <hi>CANDLESTICK.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>THE THIRD CHVRCH.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>In the Type.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">In the Antitype.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">The Church of Pergamus.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>The Pergamine ſtate of Chriſts Church.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1. THIS <hi>was next Smyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, and the moſt Northward of all theſe three Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and ſo far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt from the Sun, ſcituate in the col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest part. And whereas Sathan in Epheſus had falſe Apoſtles in Smyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, a Synagogue, heere bee hath a Throne.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1. THis ſtate was next after the other, from after <hi>Gratian</hi> his time more darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by little and little, and more corrupt then the other, till the Throne of Sathan was erected in <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſo euery thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came worſe and worſe, till be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the 11. and 12. hundreth yeare. <hi>Plat. in vit. Bonifa. 3.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2. <hi>This Perga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus was the most famous and head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie of Aſia, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, Decad. 4. l. 7. Plin. nat. hiſt. l. 5. c. 30. where the</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>2. So this <hi>Pergamine</hi> ſtate was vnder the power of <hi>Rome,</hi> the moſt famous and head-citie of the World, where the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Emperours had ruled till <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, and which</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:14"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>ſeate of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane iuriſdiction was for thoſe parts, after that the King of Pergamus called Attalus Philome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, had made the people of Rome his Heire, Iornand. de Reg. ſucceſſ. In this Citie and vnder the power thereof was the Angell and the Church of Chriſt planted.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>as yet was the chiefe Citie of all the <hi>Romane</hi> power.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3. <hi>To this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell Chriſt ſheweth him ſelfe with a ſharpe two-edged ſword, threatning to fight with it againſt the Enemy, verſe 16.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>3. Becauſe he would affoord his Angels, and faithfull Paſtors the ſame in his time, to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the enemies thereof.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4. <hi>Heere was the Throne of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than ſet vp, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>topping this Angell and Church.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>4. So Sathan in this ſtate of the Church, erected vp at <hi>Rome</hi> his Throne, when hee made the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> Pope, vniuerſall Biſhop, and ſo. That Antichriſt; which Supremacie the Biſhoppe of that Sea euer ſought after, and obtayned at length by <note n="a" place="bottom">Bed. in lib. de temp. Plat. in vita Bonifa 3. Blond. Decad. 1. l. 9. Sleid. de 4. Imper. l. 2. Paulus Warnfri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus l. 4. de geſtis Lomb.</note> 
                           <hi>Phocas.</hi> And thus he crept into that Throne. Firſt, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolling <hi>Rome</hi> as the head-citie of the Empire, kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping euer on foot the honour thereof. Secondly, by <hi>Conſtantines</hi> remoouing and building <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> and afterwards in <hi>Iuſtinus</hi> dayes when the <note n="b" place="bottom">Blond. l. 8. Dec. 1. Seid. de 4. Imp. l. 2.</note> 
                           <hi>Exarch</hi> was eſtabliſhed, which Magiſtrate left <hi>Rome,</hi> and abode moſt at <hi>Rauenna,</hi> by which el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow-roome at <hi>Rome,</hi> the Pope crept vp more and</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:15"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>more. Thirdly, by neglecting to come <note n="c" place="bottom">Socrat. l. 2. c. 5. Sleid. de 4. Imp. lib. 2. vid. Exemplar. Leonis PP. ad Theodoſ. 2. &amp; Martia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, Imp. tom. 2. Conciliorum.</note> perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally vnto generall Councels from his owne place, not ſtanding vpon his owne authoritie, as not bound to come, but making excuſes, ſomtimes one thing, ſometimes an other thing, and ſo craftily kept away, and ſent only his Legates with Letters of excuſe; which pride of his either not percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued or neglected, hee made after-aduantage of. Fourthly, by his wealth which began to bee great from the time of the Biſhop <hi>Marcellus,</hi> as ſome <note n="d" place="bottom">Polydor. l. 1. de in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent. c. vlt.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port. Fiftly, By ſuch Biſhops of the Eaſt Church, as had recourſe to <hi>Rome</hi> in their troubles, as <note n="e" place="bottom">Socrat. l. 2. c. 8. 11. 13. 14. 18. l. 4. c. 11 17. Euag. l. 3. c. 15. 21.</note> 
                           <hi>Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> often, <hi>Paulus</hi> of <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantinople, Aſclepas</hi> of <hi>Gaza, Marcellus</hi> of <hi>Ancyra,</hi> with others of the Orthodox Faith. So <hi>Macedonians</hi> Sectaries; all which the Pope entertayned, as thereby ſeeing his place ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced, and by which he tooke no ſmall aduantage to lift vp himſelfe, and to become great (the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> Emperour either ignorantly furthering, or wiſely hindering his proud aſpiring ſpirit) taking vpon him a claime of Superioritie ouer others, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaging a <note n="f" place="bottom">Sleid. de 3. Imp. l. 2.</note> Canon of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Councell for his authoritie, but falſly: by all which helpe and meanes he tooke vpon him, Firſt, <note n="g" place="bottom">So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crat. l. 2. c. 11. 13.</note> to reprehend other Biſhops beyond his iuriſdiction. Secondly, <note n="h" place="bottom">Euag. l. 3. c. 8.</note> to depriue ſome. Thirdly, <note n="i" place="bottom">Sleid. de 4. Imp. l. 2. Niceph. l. 13. c. 34.</note> to excommunicate euen <hi>Arcadius</hi> the Emperor of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> of</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:15"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>which Act of Pope <hi>Innocent,</hi> 
                           <note n="k" place="bottom">Anno Chriſti 407.</note> 
                           <hi>Baronius</hi> maketh mention in his Annals, and ſo of diuers other Popes excommunicating Emperours, yea, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming farther, he challenged <note n="l" place="bottom">So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crat. l. 7. c. 11.</note> Secular power; and as he got authority, ſo to hold the ſame with ſome ſhew of Antiquity, and as his right, <note n="m" place="bottom">Sleid. de 4. Imp. l. 2.</note> teſtimonies of <hi>Greeke</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi> Fathers haue bin pretended, Epiſtles forged, Canons fayned, and Councels fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſified. For many particulars let the Reader peruſe Maſter Doctor <hi>Sutcliffe,</hi> his Abridgment or Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey of Popery, <hi>c. 23. &amp; 24. &amp; Doctor Field his fift Booke of the Church, c.</hi> 33. 34. 35. 36. And thus was Sathans Throne exalted in this <hi>Pergamine</hi> ſtate.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5. <hi>In this was one Antipas, a Martyr.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>5. In this time, were many Antipaſſes Martyrs, ſuch as were <hi>Antipapae</hi> againſt the proud Pope</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:16"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>of <hi>Rome,</hi> who now to vphold his vſurped authoritiy, ſhed the bloud of many holy Saints; of which they that deſire Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, let them reade Doctor <hi>Sut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliffe</hi> his fore-named Booke, <hi>c.</hi> 44. Doctor <hi>Vſher. Hist. Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, de Christianae Eccleſie conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nua Succeſsione, &amp; Fox his. Acts and Monuments.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6. <hi>In this were ſuch as held faſt Chriſts Name, and did not deny the Faith.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>6. In all this time there were ſuch as held out the Truth, ſo as the faith of Chriſt was preſerued by them, euen vnto our times, as Doctor <hi>Vſher</hi> in his Booke main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth. <hi>Morney in his Mystery of Iniquity.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7. <hi>In this were there ſuch as vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held Balaams Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, prouoking to Idolatry &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall vncleanneſſe and the ſinne of the Nicolaitans.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>7. In this ſtate the <hi>Balaams</hi> Doctrine of <hi>Rome</hi> was mightily defended, Imagery and Idolatry maintayned, and hither-to vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held; and for corporall filthines it is needleſſe to cite teſtimonies, fot after that the Popes forbad Marriage to the Clergie, enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſingle life, allowed Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines and tolerated Stewes, the</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:16"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>World was filled with ſuch fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe, as a Chriſtian abhorreth to name. See proofes in Doctor <hi>Sutcliffes</hi> fore-named Booke, <hi>c.</hi> 29. 30. But how contrary <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſius</hi> the Emperour, was to the Popes receiuing Tribute from the Whores, reade <hi>Euag. l. 3. c. 39 Pau. Diacon. l. 21. 23. Baron. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. Carol. Magd. l. 4. c. 11. Hist. Madg. cent. 8. c. 10. Epist. Adrian. PP. ad Imper. &amp; Imperat. Irenam. Lu. Oſian. Epit. Cent. l. 4. Cent. l. 8. c. 5. Iuels defence of his Apol. 4. part, p. 344.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8. <hi>This Angell &amp; Church is thret ned to haue the LORD to come quickly to them, and againſt the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies with his two-edged Sword.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>8. So indeed the Lord came ſhortly, after this Throne erected at <hi>Rome,</hi> vnto this <hi>Pergamine</hi> like Church; which ſuffered great affliction with the reſt of the World: But <hi>Rome, Italy,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts of the <hi>Romane</hi> Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction were plagued with the Sword of the <hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
                           <hi>Gothes, Vandals, Hunnes,</hi> and other <hi>Barbarians,</hi> &amp; after with the <hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                           <hi>Saracens,</hi> and then with the <hi>Turkes,</hi> the ſcourge</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:17"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>of Chriſtendome; and at length the Lord with the Sword of his mouh, ſet vpon the Antichriſt of <hi>Rome,</hi> as in the next ſtate of the Church is cleerly ſhewed. <hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
                           <hi>Eutrop. l. 13. Blond. l. 1. Decad. &amp; l. 2. &amp; 3. Oroſ. l. 7. c. 37. Procopode bello Goth. <hi rend="sup">e</hi> Blond. l. 10.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Hee that hath an care let him eare what the Spirit ſaith to the Churches; for great ſhall be their reward who ouer come, euen to eate of the hidden Manna, to haue the White Stone, and a new name written there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>And thus much for the ſtate of the Church, from <hi>Gratian</hi> to the yeare 1100. and odde, ſet out by the Church of <hi>Porgamus.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14154:17"/>
                  <head>CONSIDERATIONS FOR INSTRVCTION <hi>AND VSE.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FIrſt, that Sathan will ſtriue for Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, hee will haue his Throne; neither he nor his are willing to bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derlings. Secondly, that where the very Throne of Sathan is, there yet may bee ſome people belonging to the Lord. Thirdly, that the faithfull hold faſt their profeſſion in the midſt of perſecution, and will not deny the Truth. Fourthly, that the Enemies of the Truth are of a murthering diſpoſition, they will ſlay and ſhed the bloud of the Saints. Fiftly, that it is a fault in a Church (though o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe prayſe worthy) to haue ſuch in her as openly teach contrary to the Truth, to corrupt the true Worſhip of God, and a Chriſtian Conuerſation. Sixtly, That the Sword of CHRISTS mouth is the weapon to fight againſt falſe Teachers with.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:14154:18"/>
               <head>THE FOVRTH GOLDEN <hi>CANDLESTICK,</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>THE FOVRTH CHVRCH.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>In the Type.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">In the Antitype.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">The Church of Thyatira.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>The Thyatirean ſtate of the Church.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1. <hi>THis is next to Perga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, ſituate from it Eaſt-ward, and ſo turning towardes the Sunne.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1. THis ſtate is next the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and becommeth better then it was, beginning from after the 1100. and odde yeares, when the Lord rayſed vp the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> vnto <hi>Luthers</hi> time, 1516.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2. <hi>To this, Chriſt ſheweth himſelfe to bee the Sonne of God, with eyes of flaming fire, and feet of Braſſe.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>2. Becauſe in this ſtate of the Church he ſhewed himſelfe to be ſo, and for that hee would giue light of vnderſtanding to many, and expel the groſſe dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe from them, and tread down powerfully his enemies, &amp; make his ſeruants to abide durable like Braſſe in the furnace of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, againſt the <hi>Ieſabel</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:18"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3. <hi>This is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended largely for vertues, and to be better at the laſt, then at the firſt, contrary to Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>3. Such God raiſed vp in this ſpace of time worthy praiſe, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he qualified with many Graces, Charity, Seruice, Faith, Patience, and Works worthy amendment of life, as may bee ſeene in thoſe <hi>Waldenſes</hi> and <hi>Albigenſes,</hi> who ſpred the Truth into all parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> ſo many of all ſorts em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced the ſame, and ſtood con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly in the Truth, and were readie to dye for it againſt the Pope, and his tyrannicall power, purſuing them with fire and ſword: but when the Lord ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp <hi>Iohn Wickliffe,</hi> and after him <hi>Iohn Huſſe,</hi> and <hi>Ierome</hi> of <hi>Prage,</hi> the Church of Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came much more excellent, and daily better and better: the Lords hand at this time helping by the Art of printing, found out by a <hi>Germane,</hi> in <hi>Anno 1440. Acts &amp; Monu. of the Hiſtory of the Wald. p. 209. Doctor Vſher lib. de Eccleſ. Chriſt. Succeſ. c. 8. 9. 10. Of the Martyrs then ſee Fox his</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:19"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Acts &amp; Mon. p. 387. Funct. Chron. p. 159. 160. Bucholtz. Chronol. Nauclerus Catal. test. veritatis. Sleid. de 4. Imp. l. 3. p. 346. Polydo. Virg. l. 2. c. 7. de inuentione rerum.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4. <hi>Heere was the woman Ieſabel ſeducing the people to Idolatry, &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall vncleannes.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>4. Heere was the <hi>Romane</hi> Church now become a <hi>Ieſabel,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſing Kings to take her part, ſetting vp <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets: but putting to death the Prophets of God, murthering the Saints of God, but vphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as before Idolatry, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing fleſhly vncleanneſſe as is ſhewed in the <hi>Pergamine</hi> ſtate, &amp; for this ſee <hi>Sixtus quartus</hi> his al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance of Sodometry; but for the ſpirituall Adultery of this Whoriſh Church, euery ſtocke and ſtone, their madde running on pilgrimage to this hee, that ſhe-ſaint, proclaimeth the ſhame thereof to the World. <hi>La. Oſiand. Epit. Centur. l. 3. c. 4. cent. 15. Agrip. de vanit. Scient. c. 64. de leonina. Weſellus Gron. de indulg. Papalibus, cited by Morn.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:19"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>in propoſ. 64. of his Myſt. of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5. <hi>This was threatned to bee caſt into a Bed, her Fauourites &amp; Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers into great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flistion, and to kill her children with death.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>5. And indeed this Harlot at this time fell ſick of a Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of which euer ſince ſhee hath languiſhed; vpon Kings and Princes her Louers, the Lord brought great afflictions, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time through the factions of the Popes, ſometime by their taking vpon them to take Kingdomes from one, and to giue them to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, other-while by Kings and Princes falling out one with another among themſelues, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was it a light tribulation that fell vpon the Kings and Princes ſubiect to the Pope, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at his command they muſt arme themſelues either one againſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, if he pleaſed to hold any for Heretickes, or did excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate any or held any to bee diſobedtent to his luſts; or ioyne all againſt the <hi>Saracens</hi> to regain <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> (whilſt the Pope play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the falſe-hearted Wretch at</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:20"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>home) which coſt the liues of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue ten Millions of people, the children of that <hi>Iezabel</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> And after theſe the LORD brought the Turkiſh fury vpon thoſe Antichriſtian Kingdomes. <hi>Morn. in his Myſtery of Iniquity, ſheweth theſe things at large. Acts &amp; Mon. 183. 603 p. &amp; 675. Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus ſub In. 3. PP. Anno 1204. apud Lateranum pro recuperanda Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſ. Chron. Chronicorum. Plat. in vita Inno. 3.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6. <hi>In this Church there were ſuch as knew not the depths of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, to whom (if they hold faſt what they haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) a promiſe was made that they ſhould bee rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>6 In this Church there haue bin and yet are vnder that Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and wicked <hi>Ieſabel,</hi> ſuch as know not that Myſtery of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, the depths of that Romiſh doctrine, to whom there is hope of mercy and victory in the end, if they hold faſt the Truth which God hath reuealed vnto them.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7. <hi>There is rule and power promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed heere vnto ſuch as ſhall preuayle &amp; euercome.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>7. Heere it began to come to paſſe; for the true Church long hidden, beganne powerfully to preuayle, of which the LORD gaue ſtrong perſwaſions to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:20"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>who ſo confidently deliuered their mindes of the decay of the honour of this <hi>Ieſabel</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and how the Word of God, and the true Church of Chriſt ſhould flouriſh, as that their ſpeeches were held as Propheticall. See <hi>Morney his Myſtery of Iniquity,</hi> in the Oppoſition after the 64. Propoſition, who mentioneth <hi>Sauanarola, Weſſellus, Ioh. Oſterid. Paulus Scripto. Ioh. Keiſerb Andr. Proles, Ioh, Hilton,</hi> which laſt fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told plainly the yeare of <hi>Luthers</hi> beginning to preach. <hi>Morn. his Myſt. of Iniquity. Acts &amp; Mon. p.</hi> 768. 769. &amp; 580.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <q>Hee that hath an eare, let him heare what the Spirit ſaith to the Churches.</q>
               <p>And thus much for the ſtate of the Church, from yeares aboue 1100. vnto <hi>Luthers</hi> beginning to preach, 1516. ſet out in the Church of <hi>Thyatira.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14154:21"/>
                  <head>CONSIDERATIONS FOR INSTRVCTION <hi>AND VSE.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FIrſt, that now in this time the depth of Sathans policies began to bee v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Secondly, that maugre his malice and miſchiefe the true Church getteth ſtrength. Thirdly, that when God purpoſeth to better the eſtate of his Church, hee will qualifie his Seruants with better gifts to further his purpoſe. Fourthly, that in a ſound Reformation, the Church is not the beſt at the firſt, but groweth better and better, ſo as the laſt workes thereof are more then the firſt. Fiftly, that the tolleration of a <hi>Ieſabel,</hi> falſe Doctrine and falſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, is a foule fault in the true Church. Sixtly, that the end of Sathans Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments is to ſeduce the godly, and to bring them to commit wickedneſſe. Seuenthly, that though God giue the wicked ſpace to repent, yet will they be nothing the better for it. Eighthly, that not only the chiefe Authours of euill,
<pb facs="tcp:14154:21"/> but ſuch as conſent to them are lyable to the ſame iudgement, except they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. Ninthly, that neither <hi>Ieſabel</hi> with her Abettors, nor yet the depths of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan can hinder the Churches increaſe in wel-doing, when God wil aide her with his Grace. Tenthly, that there may be many, where the falſe Church is which may bee ignorant of the depth of that ſinfull ſtate. Eleuenthly, that the Truth, which we receiue muſt be held faſt vnto the end.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:14154:22"/>
               <head>THE FIFT GOLDEN <hi>CANDLESTICK.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>THE FIFT CHVRCH.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>In the Type.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">In the Antitype.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">The Church of Sardis.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>The Sardine ſtate of Chriſts Church, the first of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1. <hi>THis was next after Thyatyra ſtill Eaſt ward, farther from the North.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1. THis was the next after the <hi>Thyatirian</hi> ſtate, at the end whereof this beganne more cleerely to breake out by the light of Truth, about the yeare 1516. when <hi>Luther</hi> began to preach, and continued to the yeare, 1558.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2. <hi>In this is no mention, as in the former, of Balaam, Nicolaitans, thron of Sathan, or Ieſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>2. Becauſe now the Church was come out of Romiſh Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon; for neither <hi>Balaam</hi> that falſe Prophet of <hi>Rome,</hi> nor the filthy <hi>Nicolaitans</hi> of that Seate, nor that <hi>Ieſabel</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> had any thing to doe with this Church of Chriſt, which the Lord by <hi>Luther</hi> and other fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:22"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>men brought out from that Spirituall bondage, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee did the Children of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> by <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> with a ſtrong hand, and out-ſtretched arme. <hi>Sleid. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Fox his Acts &amp; Mon. p. 767 768. &amp;c.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3. <hi>In this Chriſt ſetteth out himſelfe by the ſeuen Stars, and ſeuen Spirits of God.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>3. For that now hee would rayſe vp many learned Miniſters of the Goſpell, who as Starres ſhould ſhine and giue light to ſuch as ſhould ſit in darkneſſe, and to whome hee would giue plentifully the Graces of his Spirit to ſet forth his Truth: as he did to <hi>Luther, Zuinglius, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthon, Oecolampadius, Bucer,</hi> and to many bright Starres of his Truth in <hi>Wittenberge,</hi> in <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetia,</hi> and other places. <hi>Sleid. Comment. Lu. Oſiand. Cent. 16. Fox his Acts &amp; Monuments, p. 773.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4. <hi>This had a name to bee aliue, but was dead:</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>4. This comming from vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Antichriſt, had a name to be aliue, and to bee a Reformed</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:23"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Smyrna had not ſo good a name as ſhee deſerued, but this a much better then ſhe is worthy of.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Church in <hi>Luthers</hi> dayes, but ſhe became as dead, being farre from that life of Grace, which ſhould haue beene in her, and from that liuely reformation, which the Lord required at her hands. For howſoeuer the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches acquite themſelues of the Pope, and were no more the children of that <hi>Ieſabel</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> yet retayned they ſuch corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and errors, and at this day ſo vphold them, as their ſtate is rather dying, then liuing, except they returne. <hi>See the Booke of Concord, and the Augustane Confeſsion.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5. <hi>The workes of this were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>5. So was and is this of the <hi>Lutherans</hi> reformation, as may appeare by the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them and other Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches, in that which is commonly called <hi>Lutheraniſme,</hi> the points whereof may bee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of their Bookes, of the body of Diuinity, their <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtane Confeſsion,</hi> and Diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:23"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>againſt vs, by which may appeare their imperfect workes, vnworthy a Church Reformed, and that bleſſed Inſtrument <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> that <hi>Lucifer</hi> and bright Starre of Light, who did ſhine well in the dawning of the day, before the Sun-ſhine of Truth aroſe, and ſpred out his beames to his after followers, for them to ſee more cleerly, if they would not haue winked and ſhut their eyes, againſt the Light ſhining vpon them. <hi>See Reneccius his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noplia. Brentius, Iac. Andraeas, Seluec. &amp; Chemniſius. Lu. Oſiand. Epit. Cent. l. 3. cent. 16. c. 30.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6. <hi>This is threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for the defects and the Lord ſaith, that hee will come ſudde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly vpon them.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>6. And indeed ſo did the Lord come vpon theſe. Hee ſent a new, and ſtrange kind of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, called the <hi>Sweating Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> which in a ſhort ſpace with an incredible ſwiftneſſe paſſed through almoſt all the parts of <hi>Germanie:</hi> they were alſo great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly troubled with Warres, as may bee ſeene in that which is called</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:24"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>the <hi>Smalcaldicke</hi> Warre, made by the Emperour through the Popes inſtigation: <hi>Saxonie</hi> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued moreouer great loſſe by Fires, and alſo by horrible Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts of Thunder and Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and thus came the LORD vpon them. <hi>Sleid. Comm. Funct. Chron. Bucholc. Chron. Lu. Oſiand. Epit. Cent. l. 2. &amp; l. 3. c. 2.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7. <hi>In this Church were ſome few, which had not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed their garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>7. In this imperfect ſtate begun by the <hi>Luthera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,</hi> there were ſome which acquit themſelues more cleerely, from the Errours and Superſtitions of Antichriſt, who ſet forth a Confeſſion more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing in all things to the truth, then that <hi>Auguſtane Confeſsion:</hi> theſe were called by the <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans Sacramentaries,</hi> and <hi>Zuing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians,</hi> and afterwards <hi>Caluiniſts,</hi> for oppoſing their Conſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, and other their Errours. <hi>Sleid. Comment. Lu. Oſiand. Epit. Cent. 16.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8. <hi>Theſe in this Church were moſt</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>3: So theſe few then hath the Lord giuen honour vnto, and</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:24"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>approued of Chriſt, accounting them worthy to walke with him in white.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>approoued as worthy of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable acceptance and grace, for ſoundneſſe of Truth, and that by the conſent of many Churches agreeing therein. <hi>See the Harmonie of Confeſsions.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>9. <hi>In this is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to them that ouercome, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of Victory.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>9. Now this was very need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for thoſe times, for that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny were put vnto the tryall; not a few ſuffered baniſhment and impriſonment, for not conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the Booke of <hi>Interim,</hi> ſet out by the Emperours Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to whom many through feare yeelded, as thoſe of <hi>Wittemberge</hi> and <hi>Lipſia,</hi> who for the meane which they ſought to hold, as appeareth by the forme of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which they publiſhed, were called <hi>Adiaphoriſts,</hi> and <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtickes.</hi> Perſecution was raiſed here in <hi>England</hi> by Queene <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> by whom many were put to death for the Goſpell of Chriſt; out of <hi>Bohemia</hi> were baniſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue two hundred Miniſters of the Goſpell, and in <hi>France</hi> was a</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:25"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>grieuous Perſecution raiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe which were called <hi>Waldenſes:</hi> But for all this they ſhrunke not from the Truth, therefore the Lord will cloath them with the white garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; he will not blot out their names out of the Booke of Life, but will confeſſe them before his Father, and his holy Angels. <hi>Sleid. Com. Lu. Oſiand. Epit. l. 2. cent. 16. c. 70. 71. 72. 73. Lu. Oſian. l. 3. cent. 16. c. 20.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Hee that hath an eare let him eare what the Spirit ſaith to the Churches.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>And thus much for the ſtate of the Church from the yeare 1516. to 1558. ſet out in the Church of <hi>Sardis.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14154:25"/>
                  <head>CONSIDERATIONS FOR INSTRVCTION <hi>AND VSE.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FIrſt, that ſuch as bee come from vnder Antichriſt, may yet bee in a dying condition. Secondly, that there may bee a name of life by profeſſion, when ſuch parties may bee dead in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice. Thirdly, that where there is no care to ſtrengthen that which is good, it will dye, and euill grow vp in the roome thereof. Fourthly, That God alloweth not of the workes which are not perfect before him. Fiftly, that to amend and to be reformed, is to call our ſelues backe to the Truthes receiued. Sixtly, that God will ſurely puniſh his, if they will not otherwiſe be reformed. Seuenthly, that ſome are kept pure and vndefiled when others be ſtayned with vncleanneſſe. Eighthly, that the better part are euer the feweſt. Ninthly, that God in mercy holds them worthy of reward, which will not pollute them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with others in ſin. Tenthly, that the better men be, though neuer ſo few, the more accepted be they with God.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:14154:26"/>
               <head>THE SIXT GOLDEN <hi>CANDLESTICK.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>THE SIXT CHVRCH.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>In the Type.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">In the Antitype.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">The Church of Philadelphia.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>The Philadelphian ſtate of Chriſts Church, being the ſecond of the Reformed Churches, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from the Reigne of</hi> Elizabeth, <hi>our late Queene of happy memory, in the yeare 1558. at which time we may begin this ſixt ſtate of Christs Church, for that the Popes power began now more to bee dimini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhed then euer before, and to be caſt into ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, that hitherto he languiſheth thereof in all theſe parts of Chriſtendome; God adding the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Zeale of our learned Souereigne, by his Pen to pierce thorow the heart of his vſurped Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. The period of this not yet come, the yeare, as in all the former ſtates of the Church, cannot bee ſet downe.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1. <hi>To this Christ ſetteth out himſelf to be holy and true, to haue the Key of</hi> Dauid, <hi>to open and</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1. BEcauſe now Chriſt at this time would chiefly exalt Piety, exalt his Truth, and ſhew that as he is King, and as power belongeth to him; ſo would hee</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:26"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>none to ſhut, and to ſhut, and none to open.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>now exerciſe the ſame, that the Church might know, that hee hath taken to him his great power, and hath reigned. And indeed in what age ſince the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles time, hath true Pietie and the Truth beene more liuely ſet forth? I ſay, true Pietie and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, not that fained and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Sanctitie ſo much extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led when that <hi>Romane</hi> Beaſt did beare rule ouer all. How hath the Goſpell ſhined foorth to vs the wayes of darkeneſſe? moſt powerfully hath the Lord ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelfe by his faithfull Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, and great fruit haue they reaped of their labours; Bleſſed be his Name. <hi>cap. 11. 17.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2: <hi>Heere the LORD openeth a doore, and none ſhutteth.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>2. For now the Goſpell hath gotten free paſſage, which the Enemies by their Tridentine Councell, by their Ieſuiticall, or rather Iebuſiticall Sect, by their Seminarie Prieſts, by their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies, Trecheries, Treaſon, &amp; rayſing of Rebellion in <hi>England,</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:27"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>and <hi>Ireland;</hi> by their murthering of Princes, by their bloudy Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions in <hi>France,</hi> and moſt cruell Maſſacre, by their <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Inuaſion, by their Helliſh Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder-plot haue not beene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to hinder: ſo wide hath the Lord opened the hearts of men to receiue the Truth, as no plot, nor police of that man of ſinne hitherto hath beene able to ſhut them againſt the Truth: as it is well knowne to vs all at this day. <hi>William of Naſſ. Prince of Orenge. Hen. 4. K. of France, &amp; his Predeceſſors before.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3. <hi>This is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Chriſts Word, and for not deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Name, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing but a little ſtrength.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>3. Little was the ſtrength of the Reformed Churches in this ſtate, for not a few yeares, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the power of Princes, true vnion of hearts (Diuiſion being great betweene Lutherans and others) and Wiſedome of policie, in compariſon of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, who were ſtrongly vnited, Pope, Kings, and Princes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bining in league together, and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:27"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>all ſubtile wayes, and forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble meanes to ouerthrow the Profeſſours of the Goſpell, who yet keepe the Word of God, and did not deny the Doctrine and Worſhip of Ieſus Chriſt, to bee brought backe againe to Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. <hi>French Hiſtor. Mer. Gallobelg. Lu. Oſiand. cent. 16.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4. <hi>Chriſt to make his Lona knowne, promiſeth to this, that the counterfeit Iewes and Synagogue of Satan ſhall come &amp; worſhip at his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels feet; ſo much is now the differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of this from the Pergamine An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, who did dwell where Satans thron was.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>4. This <hi>Philadelphian</hi> ſtate of the Church through the loue of Chriſt, euen of mercie and not of any merit ſhall become moſt honourable. The Lord will ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due all her Enemies, thoſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeite Catholiques (who did reigne in the <hi>Pergamine</hi> ſtate: &amp; who, as <hi>Iewes,</hi> bragge that they are the only people of God) and will cauſe them to ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues humbly vnto the true Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of his Seruants; which wee are to expect how contrarie ſoeuer it ſeemeth to mans rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and earneſtly let vs pray for the ſame.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5. <hi>To this is</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>5. There remayneth for</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:28"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>made a promiſe of deliuerance, in the time of temptation, which is fore-told to come ouer all the World.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Chriſt his Church in this <hi>Phila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delphian</hi> ſtate, a time of tryall yet to came, our ſinnes deſerue it, &amp; this ſo vniuerſall a peace, ſo abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by carnal ſecurity may make vs looke for troubles: what this temptation is, and when it ſhall be, is not ſo certainly to be defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, except it bee that in <hi>cap.</hi> 16. 18. but be it what it may bee, let it come whenſoeuer God ſhall ſent it, the Church hath a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of deliuerance, and ſhall eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape the perill of it.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6. <hi>To this Chriſt promiſeth to come quickly, and exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it to hold faſt, that no man take away the Crown of reward.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>6. Becauſe (as may ſeeme by theſe words) the Church in this her laſt time of tryall, ſhall bee greatly aſſaulted, and in danger to periſh through the power and force of that temptation, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as the Lord promiſeth deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance, ſo hee promiſeth not to deferre it off, but will quickly ſet her free.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7. <hi>The Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer here is promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to bee made a</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>7. All this fore-ſheweth after the deliuerance from this Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation ſore-ſpoken of, that faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:28"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Pillar in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: ſo as hee ſhall goe no more out, and there ſhall be written vpon him the Name of God, and of the Citie new Ieruſalem, &amp; Christ his Name.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Chriſtians and true Church of Chriſt ſhall be in a ſtable and vnmoueable ſtate, Pope &amp; <hi>Turke</hi> the Beaſt and Dragon, open and ſecret Enemies being deſtroyed, &amp; theſe heauenly Conquerours, ſhall bee accounted the true Church of God, that new <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> ſuch as God the Father &amp; Ieſus Chriſt will claime for his owne, as if his name were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon them. <hi>C. 19. &amp; 20. &amp; C. 21. 2</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <hi>He that hath an eare let him heare what the Spirit ſaith to the Churches.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>And thus much for this beautifull and louely <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladelphian</hi> ſtate of the Church, from <hi>Anno</hi> 1558. to the time determined, ſet out in this Church of <hi>Phila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delphia.</hi> In this eſtate are we in theſe dayes.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14154:29"/>
                  <head>CONSIDERATIONS FOR INSTRVCTION <hi>AND VSE.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FIrſt, that this is the time of opening the doore that men may come into the true Church Secondly, That none now ſhall euer bee able to ſhut againe this doore, Proteſtance ſhall proſper. Thirdly, that a little ſtrength with obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Word ſhall bee ſufficient for the Churches ſafety. Fourthly, that the falſe Church, by the power of Chriſt, though this to man ſeeme incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible, ſhall be made ſubiect to the true Church. Fiftly, that ſhortly Chriſt will make the Enemies know his loue, to his owne people. Sixtly, that great tryals and temptations ſhall come vpon the World, of which, it may bee, wee haue now the beginnings, but the Lord will keepe his Church. God Almighty pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare and ſtrengthen vs, in his mercie to ſubdue our enemies, O Lord, ſaue thy people, ſhew thy power in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of thine &amp; our malicious Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, that we may for euer ſing prayſes to thy Name, euen ſo be it, O Lord, of thy goodneſſe, euen ſo be it. Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:14154:29"/>
               <head>THE SEVFNTH GOLDEN <hi>CANDLESTICK.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>THE SEVENTH CHVRCH.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>In the Type.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">In the Antitype.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">The Church of LAODICEA, the laſt of the ſeuen.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>The Laodicean ſtate of Chriſt his Church, and the laſt till Chriſt come to iudgment, which ſtate fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth vpon that height of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie and glory, which in the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladelphian ſtate it attayneth vnto.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1. <hi>HEERE Chriſt cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth himſelfe the</hi> Amen, <hi>the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and true Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the beginning of the Creation of God.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1. BEcauſe now the LORD bringeth his Church to the laſt ſtate, euen to the <hi>Amen</hi> therof hereupon Earth, in which when all things are fulfilled, which Chriſt Ieſus, as a true and faithfull Witneſſe of his Fathers will, hath foretold by himſelfe, and by his Spirit in the Prophets and Apoſtles; then ſhall he fully declare himſelfe the Authour of the heauenly Creation, and of that glory of his Saints, which they ſhall enioy with him in</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:30"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>appearing at the laſt Day. <hi>Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat. 21.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2. <hi>This became luke-warme, being neyther hote nor cold,</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>2. After the great peace which the Church ſhall haue vpon her ſo high aduancement in her for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſtate, all her Enemies being brought downe, and vtterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, ſhe ſhall decay in zeale, &amp; become luke-warme, not hot, as ſeruently bent vnto Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; neither cold, as without any affection of Religion at all, but too careleſly remiſſe in the duties of Pietie, contenting her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with a peaceable enioying of the Lords ordinances after an outward forme of Godlineſſe in abundance and plentie of all things: by which it will come to paſſe in time, that Charitie ſhall wax cold, and Faith, that is, the ſincere ſtudie of godlineſſe, ſhall ſcarcely bee found vpon Earth, when Chriſt ſhall ſhew himſelfe at his ſecond Comming. <hi>Reuel. 19 &amp; 20. Luke 18. 8.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3. <hi>The LORD</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>3. So will the Lord loath and</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:30"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>threateneth to ſpew this out of his mouth.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>abhorre the luke-warme ſtate of this Church, and caſt out the ſame for euer, in his appointed time.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4. <hi>This is taxed for glorying and for too high a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of her happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, being in a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wretched and miſerable caſe.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>4. THIS giueth vs to know, that ſuch ſhall bee the outward and flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eſtate, and plentifull bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, euery way in that reſpect, of this Church, as through the delight and full contentment thereof, they ſhall bee too igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of their ſpirituall eſtate with God, and not know how far they ſhall be from the power of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5. <hi>This is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked and chaſle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and is graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly aduiſed to vſe the meanes for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>5. Which ſheweth, that the Lord in his mercy will not bee wanting in all good meanes of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to ſeeke their reformation by word and deed, if ſo bee they will turne from luke-warmenes, and become zealous and ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend: and if they will heare him and receiue him, ſuch ſhall taſte of his ſpirituall comforts, and bee made moſt ioyfull in the</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14154:31"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>heauenly taſte thereof.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6. <hi>To him that here ouercommeth is granted a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeat with Chriſt in Heauen.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>6. There muſt bee in ſome a ſpirituall conflict, who ſhall ſtriue happily againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon current of luke-warmnes, and againſt the death of drowſie ſecurity, from which by ſtriuing they ſhall acquit themſelues, &amp; ſo graciouſly preuayling, at Chriſt his comming to reward e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one according to his works, ſhall theſe Conquerours receiue glory and honour with him in the higheſt Heauens for euer.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <q>Hee that hath an eare, let him heare what the Spirit ſaith to the Churches.</q>
               <p>
                  <hi>And thus much for this luke-warme ſtate of the Church, the laſt and fearefull condition thereof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the comming of Christ vnto Iudgement, which is not yet come vpon vs, though wee bee luke-warme enough.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14154:31"/>
                  <head>CONSIDERATIONS FOR INSTRVCTION <hi>AND VSE.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FIrſt, that as now men doe, ſo hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they will abuſe the great peace and proſperity of the Church to grow thereby ſecure. Secondly, that to bee luke-warme is the worſt diſeaſe of the Church; and that eſtate which will make the Lord to ſpew them out of his mouth. Thirdly, that full contentment of earthly things maketh men highly conceited of themſelues, and to bee ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of their ſpirituall eſtate before God. Fourthly, that men may be wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, miſerable, poore, blinde, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and yet bee highly conceited of their well being, and that they bee in a very happy condition. Of ſuch conceited perſons I wiſh this age were not full.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb facs="tcp:14154:32"/>
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>THus wee ſee apparently how the ſeuen Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> are liuely repreſentations of the ſeuen fold eſtate of the Church of Chriſt vnto the end of the World; not Types of this or that one particular Church; as ſome doe dreame, but are Types of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of the whole Church, yet ſo as there will bee a mixture, ſome thus, and ſome ſo in particular Churches, as we ſee a difference in theſe ſeuen Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches themſelues. The times of the <hi>Epheſine, Smyrnean, Pergamine, Thya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirean,</hi> and <hi>Sardine</hi> are paſt, this is now the <hi>Philadelphian</hi> ſtate, in which the Goſpell hath gotten free paſſage and muſt get; for Chriſt hath opened, and none can ſhut, howſoeuer the Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary may attempt to hinder and ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to ouerthrow the Profeſſours of the Goſpell: yet ſhall theſe our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies be ouercome, and bee made at laſt to ſubmit vnto vs; ſure it is that great tryalls ſhall be, and whether this
<pb facs="tcp:14154:32"/> preſent diſtraction of all the face of Chriſtendome, be the houre of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to try them that dwell vpon the Earth, it is to me vncertayne; but cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it is, that the Church God will preſerue, and make her renowned, and this will he doe ſhortly; for the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie is vnder the Vials of Gods wrath, as it is apparant in <hi>Chap.</hi> 16. and what did this Meſſenger from Heauen, the mighty Comet foreſhew? but theſe Warres, and good ſucceſſe thereby to the Church. For the Comets now for the yeares ſince <hi>Luthers</hi> time haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, with troubles, yet foretold good proſperity to the Goſpell. The date of the increaſe of <hi>Romes</hi> glory was out long ſince, and now is the time of the Churches increaſe daily till the ruine of <hi>Rome;</hi> which as it is fore-told in this Propheſie of Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> ſo ſhall it come to paſſe, &amp; in all probable conie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, is very neere at hand. This may we vndoubtedly look for. The deuiſes of that man of ſin, the <hi>Machauilian</hi> poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Viperous generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Ieſuits,</hi> nor all the power of <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent
<pb facs="tcp:14154:33"/> it, for the Word of the LORD hath ſpoken it, and Heauen and Earth ſhall periſh, before one <hi>Iota</hi> of the Truth ſhall fayle. Herein let vs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage our ſelues, againſt the crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our Aduerſaries, who ſee not deſtruction before them, as in this Propheſie of S. <hi>Iohn</hi> is plainly fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhewed.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:14154:33"/>
            <head>THE HONOVR OF <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F this Church &amp; Spouſe of Chriſt thus ſet out in the ſeuen-fold eſtate thereof, the Lord of his mercie hath made vs of this Nation a moſt liuely member, and aboue other Countries hath maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly ennobled this Iland, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Kingdome of great <hi>Brittaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, though wee liue farre off, in theſe Northerne parts from <hi>Iudea,</hi> yet very ſhortly after our Sauiours Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the Goſpell of God was brought vnto vs; and by whom! was it not by <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Aramathea,</hi> the onely rich and noble Counſellor, that did the firſt honour to our Lord Ieſus after his death, in begging of his body, and
<pb facs="tcp:14154:34"/> burying it in his own Sepulchre, where before neuer any was laid. This man was the Ambaſſadour (as Stories wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) from Chriſt to vs, here hee alſo vouchſafed to liue, and here among vs peaceably to end his dayes.</p>
            <p>Greatly did the Lord honour vs in giuing to vs the firſt King that euer was Chriſtian, named <hi>Lucius,</hi> who ſubmitted his Crowne and Scepter vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Was not <hi>Conſtantine</hi> called the Great, the firſt Chriſtian Emperour? and did not he ariſe from hence? was he not here borne, and here proclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Emperour? who ſlew the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Tyrants, and deſtroyed the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Enemies of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>The firſt famous Scholler &amp; publick Profeſſour of Diuinity oppoſing Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, was it not our learned and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Iohn Wickliffe?</hi> By whoſe Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings ſpred into <hi>Bohemia,</hi> (by occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Marriage betweene one of our Kings here, and that Kings Daughter) ſprung vp the renowned Martyrs <hi>Iohn Huſſe,</hi> and <hi>Ierome</hi> of <hi>Prage.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14154:34"/>
            <p>The firſt King, like valiant <hi>Iehu,</hi> marching as it were againſt the <hi>Ieſabel</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> that abſolutely ſhooke off the Popes Supremacie, that vſurped Power, and <hi>Luciferian</hi> Pride of that man of ſin, and trod it vtterly vnder his feete, was <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth? and yet for all that dyed he in peace.</p>
            <p>The firſt King, that was but a child, and yet ſet vp the true Worſhip of God, and baniſhed Popery out of his Kingdome was our King <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixt, that noble Prince, a very <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> full of the loue and zeale of his God.</p>
            <p>The firſt Princeſſe, at whoſe riſing the power of the Popedome began to abate, which ſuffered Perſecution for the Goſpell, which ſo conſtantly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended it, as being to death, <hi>ſemper ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem,</hi> at home and abroad, was it not the euerlaſtingly renowned the late Queene, our Dread Souereigne <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth?</hi> Was not She a Succour to the Saints, and a Terror to all her Enemies round about?</p>
            <p>The firſt King, and ſo Learned, as hath not the like beene in the Chriſtian
<pb facs="tcp:14154:35"/> World, publiſhing by his learned Pen vnto all the Princes in Chriſtendome, that the Pope is Antichriſt, is now our Dread Souereigne LORD and King; who hath helped to poure out the fourth Viall of Gods wrath vpon the Sunne, that is, vpon the Supremacie of that Antichriſtian ſtate. The Throne of that Beaſt ſhaketh, and <hi>Romes</hi> ruine is not farre too, maugre the rage and furie of all her Supporters.</p>
            <p>Shall I heere ſpeake of our wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full preſeruations? Strangely did God ſaue his poore flocke heere from the bloudy Wolues, in the time of the ten Perſecutions, vnto the dayes of <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſian.</hi> But then, leſt it ſhould want this honour alſo, this Nation was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned with Martyrs. What ſhall I ſpeake of our late Deliuerances, ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable and vnheard off? The At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts were many and ſundry againſt our late Queene and Souereigne. How did Pope and Papal power, ſeeke to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uade her Kingdome! How did Rebels ariſe to moleſt her! How did Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors ſeeke her bloud, and many wayes
<pb facs="tcp:14154:35"/> ſought her death; yet behold the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecting hand of God, Shee dyed in peace, neither did the Enemies hand preuayle againſt her. And can the Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder Treaſon, that matchleſſe vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanie, and more then Helliſh intended cruelty be euer of vs forgotten? At one blaſt they mercileſly intended to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy and that ſuddenly, King, Prince, and State, Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth; yet ſee the mercie of our God, wee are preſerued, and in the ſnare which they made for others, was their owne feet taken. Let vs looke about &amp; ſee whether other Princes and States haue obtayned the like protection, or rather haue they not ſuffered violence at the hands of theſe Miſcreants, and beene murthered of them? It was an honour to our Nation, that wee ſtood out ſo long at firſt againſt the Iuriſdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> for it was no ſmall time ere ſhee could obtrude her vaine Ceremonies vpon vs, when other Countries were infected and had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to drinke of her cup.</p>
            <p>And it is to vs no leſſe honour, that
<pb facs="tcp:14154:36"/> wee haue ſo ſhaken off her yoke, as we are become an Aſſaile and place of ſafegard to ſuch as daily forſake her, ſo oppoſite vnto her, and ſo vexing her, as ſhe through the paine thereof ſticks not to blaſpheme the holy Doctrine and Worſhip of our God, euen God and his Tabernacle, as <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaketh; which alſo maketh her to ſtriue by all meanes poſſible aboue all the Nations to regaine vs to her, (which neuer ſhall be) or by more then <hi>Machiauilian</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies to vndermine vs, and to bring vs to deſtruction. Becauſe God hath made vs, in powring out the Vials of his wrath vpon the Earth, Sea, Riuers, and Sunne of that State, not the leaſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, and it may bee will alſo giue vs, or thoſe that belong vnto vs, that high honour to bring her to confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and to burne that Whoriſh Citie with fire; great likelihoods there is of this, but the certaintie I leaue to God, who knoweth all things.</p>
            <p>And may we not hold it an honour to our Nation, that wee ſhould bring forth men ſo Renowned, as among our
<pb facs="tcp:14154:36"/> Aduerſaries are had in high eſteeme? Haue not wee our venerable <hi>Beda?</hi> And ſhall we boaſt of <hi>Alexander de Hales,</hi> the Father of the <hi>Summiſts,</hi> called <hi>Fons vitae?</hi> or of <hi>Iohannes Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> termed <hi>Doctor Subtilis?</hi> or of <hi>Iohn Bachon,</hi> or <hi>Bachonthorpe,</hi> named <hi>Doctor reſolutus?</hi> or of <hi>Thomas Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardine,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> honoured alſo with this Title of <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor profundus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſhall I tell of our fortunate <hi>Drake,</hi> circling the whole Earth, and returning home in ſafetie? I let paſſe many things in this kind, one inſtance may ſerue for all. What an honour was this, that once the Emperour in perſon ſhould take wages and ſerue our King in his Warres. An honour neuer afforded to any other Nation in Chriſtendome.</p>
            <p>Thus, euen thus, hath God vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed vs glory, and riches, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and ſtrength. Wee can liue of our ſelues, ſuccour others wee may, and of their aide wee ſtand in little need. If valorouſneſſe of ſpirit be not
<pb facs="tcp:14154:37"/> abated, our Enemies may be made to feare. I hope as God hath thus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced vs, the glory of his Name is this day before vs, and the good of our Countrey in euery action for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement of Religion, &amp; the peace of the people.</p>
            <p>Hee that receiueth much, oweth much, and is bound to loue the more. Let mee ſay as once <hi>Moſes</hi> did, the name <hi>Iſrael</hi> being changed into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. And now</hi> (O England) <hi>what</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 10. 12.</note> 
               <hi>doth the Lord thy God require of thee, but to feare the Lord thy God, to walke in all his wayes, and to loue him, and to ſerue the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoule, to keepe his Commandements, and his Statutes, this day for thy good.</hi> That ſo (as God himſelfe wiſhed to Iſrael) it might go well with vs and with our Children for euer.</p>
            <p>Let not (O Nation thus beloued) hautineſſe and pride impoueriſh thee, let not oppreſſions bring thee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oot, and preſſe thee downe. Let not vanities put contempt vpon thee, nor
<pb facs="tcp:14154:37"/> ryot and luxurie conſume thee. Let not prodigalitie and the idle race of a diſordered route waſte thee. Let not bribery eat vp thy Iuſtice, nor wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe defile thy chaſtitie, nor worldli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe deſtroy thy charitie, nor this curſed ſelfe-loue, breake the bond of vnity, nor thy too gentle conniuencie increaſe Popery, nor the too great ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity in theſe dayes of peace eate vp thy deuotion, and make the grow in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to contempt with thy God. Be this, oh be this farre from thee, (thou the Lords Vine-yard) of whom the Lord expecteth better fruits for his ſo great goodneſſe towards thee.</p>
            <p>I hope the honourable <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Aramethea,</hi> will make thy Nobles to contemne the World, and to giue their honour vnto Chriſt. Thy <hi>Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffe,</hi> awake vp thy Cleargie to watch the Wolues, which ſeeke to deuoure thine and their flockes. Thy ſubtill <hi>Scotus,</hi> thy reſolute <hi>Bachon,</hi> thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found <hi>Bradwardine,</hi> thy <hi>Hales</hi> the <hi>Summiſt,</hi> and thy venerable <hi>Beda</hi> will cauſe thy Schooles of Learning to
<pb facs="tcp:14154:38"/> flouriſh, and prick men forward to an emulation, and to ſtriue to excell e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them in excellencies. Thy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Kings and Princes baniſhing Popery, make the zealous againſt it, that it neuer heere any more get foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting againe within thee. Thy now Dread Souereigne ſo learnedly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couering that Antichriſtian State, cauſe thy Apoſtating Children to bee aſhamed of the Whoriſh inuentions of that man of ſinne, and ſo at length diſtaſte the ſmell of the Romiſh, or rather Rammiſh Renegadoes, and leaue of their folly and madneſſe.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, thy wonderfull preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, thy plenty, thy peace, thy beautie, thy outward glory mooue vs all, from the higheſt to the loweſt, to render all prayſe and thankes poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, to the high God Creatour of Heauen and Earth, for ſuch mercies towards thee, and to endeuour our ſelues by the lawfull right and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous vſe of all the bleſſings in thee, ſtill to preſerue, yea, and to make more renowned thy name and fame
<pb facs="tcp:14154:38"/> among all the Nations, and before the face of all thine enemies. Thus wee ought to doe, let vs pray, that we all may ſo do.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:14154:39"/>
            <head>THE GREAT MY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STERY OF GODS <hi>MERCIE.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas I made mention in the beginning of the <hi>Iewes</hi> Conuerſion, I thought it not amiſſe here to inſert the verity thereof. By <hi>Iewes,</hi> I vnderſtand the naturall of-ſpring of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, Iacob,</hi> and the twelue Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs, called <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the twelue Tribes diſperſed, to whome the Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> wrote in his time, who now are<note place="margin">Iames 1. 1. 2.</note> all knowne: onely by the name of <hi>Iewes;</hi> theſe are now the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of<note place="margin">Rom. 11. 26.</note> whom the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, and theſe ſhall bee conuerted to Chriſt, and become a Nationall people, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
<pb facs="tcp:14154:39"/> the Doctrine of the Goſpell, and make profeſſion of the Lord Ieſus, as of their true <hi>Meſsiah</hi> and Sauiour with vs.</p>
            <p>This is the Myſtery of Gods Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,<note place="margin">There is a double Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. <hi>Epheſ. 6. 36.</hi>
               </note> of which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh to the <hi>Romanes.</hi> It was a myſtery that we <hi>Gentiles,</hi> ſhould bee fellow-heires with the <hi>Iewes,</hi> which they knew not off, and it is a Myſtery that the obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate <hi>Iewes</hi> ſhall returne to Chriſt, and bee viſible members of CHRISTS Church with vs <hi>Gentiles,</hi> which My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery Saint <hi>Paul</hi> would not haue vs<note place="margin">Rom. 11. 25.</note> ignorant of.</p>
            <p>The firſt Myſtery, bleſſed bee God, is made knowne in our ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; this other Myſtery ſhall alſo bee made manifeſt in time in their ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>It was not a Myſtery to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> that ſome <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſhould be conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for they had many Proſelytes: but the Myſtery was, that God would take to him Kingdomes and Nations of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> which thing they could not endure to heare off. So it
<pb facs="tcp:14154:40"/> was no myſterie to the Gentiles in<note place="margin">Act. 22. 22.</note> Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> time, that ſome of the<note place="margin">Luk. 20. 16.</note> Iewes then, and afterwards ſhould beleeue in Chriſt, for they had exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of thouſands of Iewes conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: but the myſterie was and yet is this, which the Apoſtle would haue the Gentiles know, that the obſtinate Iewes, euen the Nation of them ſhould in time turne againe to Chriſt, and profeſſe his Name publikly with vs.</p>
            <p>This is a truth beleeued, long ſince<note place="margin">Very many learned hold it.</note> profeſſed, and by learned men of late maintayned, as may bee ſeene in the Commentaries of very many, which haue written vpon the 11. chapter to the Romanes, and on the 7. chapter of the Reuelation of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohn,</hi> whoſe names I here omit to recite, becauſe I ſtay not vpon mens aſſertion (though the voyce of ſo many learned is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great inducement) but vpon ſuch reaſons and proofes of Scripture, as may perſwade to the faith of this Truth.</p>
            <p>And firſt, who can conſider of the
<pb facs="tcp:14154:40"/> wonderfull hand of God, in their ſo<note place="margin">Their miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may moue to beleeue it.</note> miraculous preſeruation to this very day, now for the ſpace of almoſt 1600. yeares, in the great confuſion of States, but the ſame may lead him to an expectation of their future good? They bee here and there diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed, they dwell but by permiſſion whereſoeuer: yet haue they not been ſwallowed vp of Nations, nor ſo mingled, but that they be a knowne diſtinct people by name ſeuered from all others. This is ſo ſtrange a preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation for ſo long a time, as the like hath not befallen to any other vnder the whole heauen.</p>
            <p>Where was there euer a Nation, ſuch a people, ſo wholly caſt out of their Countrey, and after diſperſed, which hath not beene ſwallowed vp and loſt, but theſe? This prouidence ſo ſingular muſt needs prognoſticate ſome future good. For was not the Iewes preſeruation in their diſperſing abroad by their Babylonian captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, in an 127 Prouinces for this end, to bring them in the appointed time
<pb facs="tcp:14154:41"/> into Iudea againe? And for what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end is this ſo long preſeruation of them, but to recall them, and to make them his people, in his good time? The Iſraelites, the ten Tribes, called the Kingdome of Iſrael, were remoued by the Aſſyrian, &amp; becauſe God would not bring them to that Kingdome againe, as God brought the Iewes from Babylon, their place was loſt, and they diſperſed, ſoone became they an vnknowne people, without diſtinction mingled among<note place="margin">No Iſraelites now but vnder the name of Iewes.</note> the Nations, and are none of them at this day (though there be otherwiſe fabulous narrations hereof) but ſuch as go vnder the name of Iewes, which howſoeuer ſo called, are of all the Tribes of Iſrael. For it is ſaid in <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra</hi> 7. 7. that there went vp of the children of Iſrael with him to Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, and Saint <hi>Iames</hi> writeth to the twelue Tribes diſperſed, which hee well knew to bee then in the world, elſe hee would not haue ſo written to them. And yet in all the Acts of the Apoſtles, onely we heare of the name
<pb facs="tcp:14154:41"/> of Iewes, vnder which name and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom there were of all the<note place="margin">Rom. 11. 1. 25. 26.</note> twelue Tribes, which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth by the name of Iſrael. And in the Prophets it is ſhewed that the two Nations ſhould come to be one, the ten and two Tribes make one people, and ſo the twelue Tribes to be vnder one name. And therfore in the Iewes conuerſion is alſo the conuerſion of the Iſraelites, &amp; ſo the twelue Tribes. What if they cannot rehearſe their<note place="margin">It is not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary they ſhould know diſtinctly their Tribes.</note> Genealogies, and ſet down now their Tribes diſtinctly? There is now no neceſſitie of it, the reaſons of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct keeping of tribe from tribe, are taken away. And where is it prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied that in their conuerſion they are to bee knowne by Tribes diſtinctly? The twelue may bee, and that vnder one name, which is enough to make good the prophecie, that Iſrael ſhall be ſaued.</p>
            <p>Beſides this ſo wonderfull a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation,<note place="margin">Their increaſe is great, on <hi>Rom. 11. 25.</hi>
               </note> there is another thing to moue vs, to thinke God will bee with them, euen their exceeding encreaſe;
<pb facs="tcp:14154:42"/> for as <hi>Beza</hi> relateth from an vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall ſpeech out of Aſia and Africa, that they are ſo multiplyed, as that yet the bleſſing of <hi>Abraham,</hi> to haue his ſeede after the fleſh to be innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, is plainely ſeene vpon them, preparing them for the conqueſt of their owne Countrie, when the Lord ſhall aſſemble them together for that end. For our better aſſurance and ſettling of our hearts herein, let mee ſet before you, how the Apoſtle ſheweth this plainely in the Epiſtle to the Romanes, chap. 11. and how it is alſo confirmed in many other places of the new Teſtament.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Rom. 11. Chapt.</head>
               <p>THe ſcope of this Chapter is to<note place="margin">Scope of the Chapter.</note> proue, that God hath not finally caſt away his people the Iewes, or Iſrael his people, <hi>Verſ. 1.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſcope the Apoſtle proueth by the conuerſion of ſome then in his time, and by the conuerſion of the reſt, though then left in their obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy,
<pb facs="tcp:14154:42"/> when God ſhould call them.</p>
               <p>Of the conuerſion of thoſe in his time, he ſpeaketh in Verſes 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. giuing an inſtance firſt of himſelfe, and then of others, whom he calleth the remnant then ſaued, in ſo general a caſting off of al the Nation, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time it fell out in the dayes of <hi>Eliah,</hi> which remnant ſo ſaued, were ſo, not for their workes, but they were ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued according to the election of grace and of Gods foreknowledge.</p>
               <p>Of the conuerſion of the other in the time to come, whom hee calleth <hi>the reſt,</hi> in Verſe 7. the Apoſtle alſo doth aſſure vs, though for that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time, and now euen at this day, they bee blinded, as was foretold in the Prophets, and in the Pſalmes, <hi>Verſes</hi> 8, 9, 10. The ſumme of all that which is in the Chapter concerning theſe ſo blinded and hardened, hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto is this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the reſt of Iſrael left in their</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The ſumme of the Chapter.</note> 
                  <hi>obſtinacy for a time, were not finally caſt off, that they and their ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding poſteritie ſhould vtterly periſh:
<pb facs="tcp:14154:43"/> God forbid,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>but that in the Lords time, when the fulneſſe of the Gentiles ſhall come in, all Iſrael ſhall be ſaued,</hi> that is, <hi>as thoſe which were before the reiection of the Nation were, and as thoſe remnant choſen out in Saint Pauls time; ſo ſhall the harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and ſtiffe-necked Iewes left of God, in the appointed time returne to God.</hi> Euen the Nation of the Iewes, called Iſrael, ſhall be ſaued. For ſo Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael is to be vnderſtood, in <hi>cap.</hi> 10. 21. where hee taketh occaſion to enter vpon this diſputation, and ſo alſo in <hi>cap. 11. verſ.</hi> 7. and in <hi>verſ.</hi> 26. where he concludeth the point.</p>
               <p>That the Apoſtle meanes the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy<note place="margin">By Iſrael is meant the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of that Nation.</note> of the Iewes, it is plaine by this, that he ſpeaketh of their <hi>fall</hi> and <hi>ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> in <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. both which words hee expoundeth himſelfe. <hi>Fall</hi> is in <hi>verſ.</hi> 15. interpreted <hi>caſting away,</hi> and <hi>fulneſſe,</hi> the receiuing of them, in the ſame verſe. Now the fall and caſting of them off, was from a viſible and nationall being of Gods people and Church, therefore their receiuing
<pb facs="tcp:14154:43"/> muſt bee vnderſtood, by the Law of Oppoſites, of their being a viſible Church of Chriſt, and a Nationall people, profeſſing the true God and worſhip of his Name. And as <hi>the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting off</hi> is meant of naturall Iewes &amp; Iſraelites, the poſteritie of Iſrael and the twelue Patriarchs, ſo muſt <hi>the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing of them</hi> be vnderſtood in like ſort, for elſe ſhould not the Law of Oppoſites be kept, neither ſhould the Apoſtles diſcourſe haue dependancy of one thing with another.</p>
               <p>But leſt this truth might yet bee doubted of, the bleſſed Apoſtle doth not onely affirme it, but doth alſo confirme it by very many reaſons, ſuch as followeth.</p>
               <p n="1">1 From <hi>the end of their ſtumbling;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſ. 11.</note> they ſtumbled not to fall, and ſo to riſe no more: God forbid, ſaith the Apoſtle, that we Gentils ſhould haue ſo deſperate a conceit of them. The end was, ſaith he, not their deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but our ſaluation; for this the Lord pleaſed to make, as a way, to bring to vs the Goſpell, and to make
<pb facs="tcp:14154:44"/> vs his people, which the Iewes in their ſtanding did hinder, did oppoſe, and no way could endure to heare of. <hi>Acts 22. 22. 1. Theſſ. 2. 16.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. From <hi>the end of our Conuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſe 11.</note> alſo, which is in time to bring them backe againe vnto the Lord, by prouoking them to iealouſie: of which <hi>Moſes</hi> fore-told, <hi>Deutrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, 32. 21.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">III. From <hi>the great good which</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſe 12.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall come to vs by their recalling,</hi> euen to enrich vs the more in grace. This the Apoſtle doth proue by an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>à Minori ad Maius.</hi> For, ſaith he, if their fall and dimiſhing brought to vs ſaluation, how much more then ſhall their returne in fulneſſe bring vs riches and glorie. So then it is thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene vs and them. Their fall was to bring vs to God, our Conuerſion is appointed in time to prouoke them to returne, and this their returne will increaſe our happineſſe.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. From <hi>the Apoſtles magnifying</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſe 13. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>his office, and from his endeuour in his Miniſterie among the Gentile,</hi> ſeeking
<pb facs="tcp:14154:44"/> to winne theſe to prouoke them, and to ſaue at the leaſt ſome of them, though as yet in his time, hee could not recouer the Nation, yet hee ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at that, which hee knew ſhould be. Which endeuour he preſſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe<note place="margin">Verſe 15.</note> vnto, from the conſideration of the good to vs Gentiles, called the reconciling of the World, and from the wonderfull worke of God in them, whoſe recouery ſhall be as the rayſing vp people from the dead, of which <hi>Ezechiel</hi> the Prophet ſpeaketh in chap. 37.</p>
               <p n="5">V. From <hi>the hereditarie right</hi> to<note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſe 16.</note> be Gods people, holy to the Lord, as the ancient Iſraelites were, <hi>Ier.</hi> 2. 3. by couenant made with their firſt Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iacob:</hi> which hee ſetteth out by a double ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude, the one from the firſt fruits, which ſanctified the reſt, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the roote, the ſap whereof is carryed into the branches.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. From the humble carriage,<note place="margin">Verſe 17. to 23</note> which the Apoſtle requireth vs to ſhew towards them, as not being ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects
<pb facs="tcp:14154:45"/> and flat caſt-awayes, but as to thoſe of whoſe ingraſting in againe, there is good hope. This is the mayne ſcope of the Verſes 17. to the midſts of 23. and the particular of the words are to draw the Gentiles on to a humble behauior towards the Iewes, without any proud inſulting ouer them.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. From <hi>the poſsibilitie of their</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſe 23.</note> 
                  <hi>ingrafting in againe,</hi> from the power of God, for God is able to doe it, though this their conuerſion ſeeme neuer ſo impoſſible to man.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. From <hi>the eaſineſſe of effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſe 24.</note> 
                  <hi>it, à comparatione minoris.</hi> The Lord againſt nature grafted vs Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, cut out of the wild Oliue tree, into the good Oliue, which was a hard thing, then more eaſily ſhall they bee grafted againe into their owne Oliue tree. If wee that were none of the Church, without the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant, Aliens from the common weale of Iſrael, could be made Gods people, then much more they which were Iſraelites, hauing the adoption,
<pb facs="tcp:14154:45"/> were once in the Couenant, to whom<note place="margin">The preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues of the Iewes.</note> the Law was giuen, to whom the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice did appertaine, to whom the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes were made, they alſo deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from the holy Patriarchs, and of whom Chriſt after the fleſh came, may bee recalled home, and made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine the people of God.</p>
               <p n="9">IX. From <hi>the hidden ſecrecie of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſe 25.</note> 
                  <hi>this point,</hi> concerning the length of time, how long they the Iſraelites ſhall continue in this their obſtinacie. It was not for euer, but onely till the fulneſſe of the Gentiles ſhould come in; which thing here the Apoſtle cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth a <hi>Myſtery,</hi> whereof hee would not haue vs Gentiles ignorant.</p>
               <p n="10">X. From <hi>the Apostles owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſe 26.</note> which hee maketh vpon this Diſcourſe and large Diſpute, which is this, &amp; very confidently ſet downe, <hi>that ſo all Iſreal ſhall bee ſaued,</hi> of the meaning of which words before is ſpoken.</p>
               <p n="11">XI. From <hi>the Propheticall autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſe 26. 27.</note> out of the Old Teſtament, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telling vs of this their Couuerſion;
<pb facs="tcp:14154:46"/> as alſo is prooued before.</p>
               <p n="12">XII. From Gods loue vnto the<note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſe 28. 29.</note> Fathers, for whoſe ſake the Lord is conſtant towards you, as he that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth and beſtoweth his gifts without repentance; being ſtable, as the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt ſaith, in his Couenant, <hi>Pſal. 103. 17. 18.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">XIII. The example of Gods mercifull dealing with vs Gentiles, hee plainly concludeth the like vnto the Iewes. The Lords mercie in times paſt vnto vs Gentiles, when we were vnbeleeuers, ſhould mooue vs to be well perſwaded of the Iewes Conuerſion, though as yet they bee not beleeuers: For in this vnbeliefe, as the Apoſtle ſaith, God hath ſhut vp all, firſt, wee Gentiles, and then they the Iewes, that both might bee ſaued by Gods meere mercie. Our vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe hindred not our calling, no more ſhall their vnbeliefe hinder their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calling, ſo will God in mercy bee glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in both.</p>
               <p>To this teſtimonie of the Apoſtle to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> I will here adde other
<pb facs="tcp:14154:46"/> Witneſſes of Scripture, out of the mouth of Chriſt, and from others al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for more confirmation of this truth. The Teſtimonies of the Olde Teſtament are amply produced, by one very lately come forth, who hath alſo cited <hi>Mat. 23. &amp; 24. 2. Theſſ. 8. 8. Reuel. 1. 7. &amp; 16. 12. &amp; 19. 5. &amp;</hi> 20. 21. 22. which I therefore omit, referring the Reader to the Booke called <hi>The Worlds great reſtauration.</hi> Other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces I will heere ſpeake of to further this light, that the eyes of ſuch as ſee not, may behold how cleere this point is.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Luke 21. 23. 24.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THere ſhall be great diſtreſſe in the Land, and wrath vpon this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and they ſhall fall by the edge of the Sword, and ſhall bee led away captiue into all Nations, and Ieruſalem ſhall be trodden downe of the Gentiles, vntill the time of the Gentiles be fulfilled.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Heere our Sauiour fore-telleth, Firſt, the great miſery of that Nation
<pb facs="tcp:14154:47"/> in their owne Land. Secondly, that the Sword ſhall come vpon them, and by Warre they ſhall bee ouercome and ſlaine. Thirdly, that ſuch as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine of them ſhall become Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues. Fourthly, that they ſhall not bee lead into any one Countrey, but bee diſperſed in all Nations. Fiftly, that this treading downe of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſhall bee by the Gentiles, all theſe things are prooued infallibly true to the eyes of all the World. Sixtly, that this treading downe thereof by them is not foreuer, but for a time, <hi>vntill the times</hi> (that is, the fulneſſe, <hi>Rom. 11. 25.) of the Gentiles be fulfilled,</hi> that is, bee come in. Therefore there is a time, that the Nations ſhall bee brought backe againe, and bee made a people vnto God in the time and ſeaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Luke 1. 69. 75.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ZAcharie</hi> in this his prayſes fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telleth of Chriſts Birth, as if then borne, and then what hee ſhall bee to
<pb facs="tcp:14154:47"/> 
                  <hi>them,</hi> euen to that people, to wit, a horne of ſaluation, He that ſhall ſaue <hi>them</hi> from <hi>their</hi> Enemies, and from the hands of all that hate <hi>them,</hi> and ſhall ſo ſet them free, as that <hi>they</hi> ſhall all their dayes ſerue <hi>him</hi> without feare in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe. Which Propheticall ſpeech, as it may bee ſpiritually vnderſtood of the whole Iſrael of God, ſo nothing hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth, but that this may be litterally ment of the Conuerſion of that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and of their happy condition vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Chriſt, ſeeing the Prophets fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell it, the Apoſtle prooueth it, and Chriſt himſelfe beareth witneſſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Luke 2. 32. 34.</head>
               <p>OLde Father <hi>Simeon</hi> in his pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing God, telleth how Chriſt was prepared to bee ſaluation before the face of all people, in Verſe 30. 31. then this generall ſpeech of all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, hee diuides into two heads, <hi>firſt to bee a light to lighten the Gentiles,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14154:48"/> and then to be <hi>the glorie of his people Iſrael.</hi> In thus placing one before the other, hee fore-ſhewed how Chriſt ſhould ſhine as light to the Gentiles, whoſe eyes ſhould bee opened by his ſpirit, to take him for their Sauiour, and then the fulneſſe of them being come in, hee ſhould bee a <hi>glory</hi> to Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, &amp; make them renowned &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious. Which glory as yet they haue not attayned vnto: for hitherto hee hath bin to them a ſtumbling block, &amp; a ſtone of offence, and not glory. And it is further obſeruable, that this holy man telleth the bleſſed Virgin, <hi>that Chriſt ſhall bee ſet for the fall,</hi> that is, the reiection of that Nation, as it is taken in <hi>Rom. 11. 15. and riſing againe,</hi> that is, the receiuing to grace, <hi>of many in Iſrael,</hi> The fall we ſee; the riſing of them againe wee muſt ſee in time: for God is true in the one, as well as in the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Acts 1. 6.</head>
               <p>HEre the Apoſtles, vpon the very day of Chriſts Aſcenſion, asked
<pb facs="tcp:14154:48"/> our Sauiour, <hi>whither hee would then restore the Kingdome of Iſrael?</hi> They did exſpect an outward reſtoring of ſtate and glory to their Nation. Our Sauiour doth not finde fault with the opinion, as an error, neyther denyeth hee the thing, but implyeth rather that ſuch a thing ſhould be, only the times and ſeaſons, ſaith hee, was not for them to know, which his Father had put in his owne power.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>2. <hi>Cor. 3. 16.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Apoſtle, as he taught the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes,</hi> ſo heere hee ſpeaketh of their miſerable eſtate, blindneſſe of mind, and how as yet the vaile was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer their heart, thus he ſpeakes of the Nation and whole people of the Iewes, whom he calleth the Children of Iſrael, of the blindneſſe of <hi>their minde,</hi> and of the vaile ouer <hi>their heart,</hi> his wordes are to bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood. And hauing thus ſpoken of their miſerable condition, he turneth his ſpeech to the hope of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion,
<pb facs="tcp:14154:49"/> and ſaith. Neuertheleſſe, when it ſhall turne to the Lord, that is, that <hi>Nation</hi> or the <hi>heart</hi> of that people, the veile ſhall be taken away. This ſhewes that the Apoſtle did looke for their Conuerſion, though hee could not ſet downe the time, which is, as Chriſt ſaid, kept ſecret with the Father. <hi>Acts 1. 6.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being by theſe Scriptures, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Reaſons perſwaded of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of theſe Ancient people of God, ſo much for the honour of Chriſt and our good, let vs vſe ſuch meanes as may further the ſame, euen alſo in compaſſion to their poore ſoules, and our mutuall ſolace toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.<note place="margin">Meanes to be vſed for their Conuerſion.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, To pray with all earneſt affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ſpirit, that God would in his mercy take away the veile, that lyeth ouer their hearts, to open their eyes to behold and ſee with vs their true <hi>Meſsiah,</hi> and <hi>Dauid</hi> their King, our Lord <hi>Ieſus Christ,</hi> that ſo their might bee one Shepheard and one Sheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, euen ſo. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14154:49"/>
               <p>Secondly, To ſend able inſtruments among them to reaſon with them, &amp; to write vnto them; that ſo if it were poſſible, wee might ſaue their ſoules, ſome of them in our time at the leaſt, as the Apoſtle endeuoured in his time, as we haue heard, <hi>Rom. 11. 14.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, To labour to remoue the mayne let (which hindereth chiefly their Conuerſion) that Beaſt &amp; falſe Prophet, that <hi>Romane</hi> Antichriſt, with his vſurped Dominion. For the <hi>Iewes</hi> deteſt Idolatry, and are very cunning in the Law and Prophets, where they ſee it forbidden, and ſpoken againſt, and knew that their Fore-fathers were grieuouſly puniſhed for it, and therefore they cannot imagine, that ſuch Chriſtians can bee Gods people, that liue in ſuch groſſe Idolatry, which is a continuall ſtumbling block before their eyes, to keepe them from Chriſt. Let vs therefore ſeeke the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow of that <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion, as for our owne ſoules ſafetie, the peace of Chriſtendome, ſo alſo for the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Conuerſion of this miſerable peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb facs="tcp:14154:50"/> who can neuer bee regayned to the Truth, and brought to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Chriſt, till Papiſtry be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Let vs frame our liues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, to all holineſſe and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; that ſo they may ſee our good workes, and glorifie God in the day of Viſitation, which ſhall not onely prouoke them, but ſhall redound to the amplification and improuement of our owne, both temporall and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall happineſſe; which the Lord grant, ſo bee it,</p>
               <closer>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:14154:50"/>
            <head>PEACE TO THE PVRE IN HEART. <hi>OR</hi> Good aduice to walke wiſely, <hi>to preſerue</hi> VNITIE <hi>among our</hi> ſelues, that our vnited Forces <hi>may be ſtronger against the common Enemie.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eceiue wholſome inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction thou that readeſt. If thou bee deſirous to walke in a ſtraite way, yet let it not be framed after thine own wil, but look it be the right way chalked out by Gods Word. The Golden Meane is a ſweet meaſure, when a man will bee neither fooliſhly ſuperſtitious, nor lewdly preſumptuous; the two rockes of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, the one on the right hand, the
<pb facs="tcp:14154:51"/> other on the left, menacing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. It is good to walke with an euen foot; and it is grace to endeuour to be what wee ought to bee, though wee cannot attaine to bee what wee ſhould be.</p>
            <p>Bee no Atheiſticall Securitan, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge God in all thy wayes; nor yet a Wil-worſhipper; mans corrupt will is at oddes with God; if it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe any thing in Religion as matter of worſhip, the ſame turneth to wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe.</p>
            <p>Be no fantaſticall Anabaptiſt, the true Spirit informeth the minde out of the Word: nor an Arminian the new coyned Opinioniſt: nor a Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gian an olde Hereticall Dogmatiſt: No blaſphemous Arian, nor Lulliani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Roſacrucian. Be no Schiſmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Browniſt, nor the fond and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Allegorizing Familiſt, nor any new Noueliſt, to arrogate any thing to thy ſelfe aboue others, to be an au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of new Deuices, thereby to draw Diciples after thee. Beware of Hereſie and Schiſme, hate alſo hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie
<pb facs="tcp:14154:51"/> and prophaneneſſe. Hereſie ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeth the foundation; Schiſme cuts off Communion; Hypocriſie is a painted ſhew without ſubſtance, neuer affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding inward comfort; and prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſtayneth the glory of Chriſtian profeſſion.</p>
            <p>Bee no Pſeudo-catholike doting vpon the deedes and doings of that man of ſinne. Allow antiquity; but bee not deceiued with the pretence thereof. The old way is the good way when it can be ſhewed by the Word. Traditions of men beſides the Truth often make Traytours to God. Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome not againſt conſcience is good; but it may not bee a Law to any in an ill path. Examples of men worthy imitation are not to be neglected; but their Errours and crooked treadings are not to bee oppoſed to diuine Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts. God muſt in matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion beare ſway; man is only to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther what in his worſhip he willeth to be done, and that obey readily.</p>
            <p>In the truth a man muſt bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, not a Time-ſeruer, a Proteſtant
<pb facs="tcp:14154:52"/> in earneſt, not a Laodicean Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitant, nor yet a prepoſterous Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitant: but bee diſcreetly zealous; yet ſo as diſcretion may guide, but not blunt the edge of zeale, as it doth in too many.</p>
            <p>In a word hold the ancient, Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, Orthodoxall Veritie and Truth, agreeing with the Word, and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly gain-ſay not laudable Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes of the Church, not againſt the Word. In ſuch things bee not ready to take offence and alſo be very loth iuſtly to giue offence, and thus ſhalt thou ſhew thy peaceable diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. To further thy godly inclinable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hereto, conſider well of theſe ſo friendly giuen Chriſtian Aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and wholſome Counſels of Peace. Reade (good friend) aduiſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I beſeech thee, poſt not on apace: though thou haſt a quicke apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to vnderſtand, yet take time to ſettle affection. Some good things are ſoone knowne, but in heart for the moſt part lightly intertayned: whence it is, that many do onely talke
<pb facs="tcp:14154:52"/> of that often, which not once they euer made vſe of. But my purpoſe of ſetting downe theſe things, is to bring them into practice: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo reade thou deliberatly, as thy will may bee to performe them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionably, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How a man ought to carry himſelfe in a Christian State, wiſely, peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and yet religiouſly.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, vphold the manifeſt good therein.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the manifeſt euils, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in thy place by the beſt meanes to haue them amended peaceably.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Beare with lighter faults for a time, till fit occaſion bee offered to haue them amended.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Likelihoods of euill, make them not apparent euill, by ill interpretation, where neyther the State intendeth it, nor ſo maintaynes it.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, doubtfull things take in the better part, it is euer Charity.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14154:53"/>
               <p>Sixtly, iudiciouſly diſcerne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the abuſe of a thing, and that which may bee well vſed; leſt in ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horring the abuſe, thou alſo doe vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly condemne the thing it ſelfe and the vſe thereof.</p>
               <p>Seuenthly, let the corruption of the perſon and his lawfull place bee diſtinguiſhed: and where perſon and place are not ſo lawfull, and in the propoſed end not againſt thee, wiſely labour to make them for thee; and make that good of them thou canſt, and wholly condemne not that Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery which a godly man may make for good.</p>
               <p>Eighthly, patterne not a <hi>Monarchy</hi> to an <hi>Oligarchie,</hi> nor to any other State, <hi>Aristocratie</hi> or <hi>Democratie:</hi> let not the well being of a forreine State make thee vnthankfull for the preſent good thou doeſt enioy, and to loath thine owne being, leſt malcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedneſſe breake into contention, ſo thou loſe that good thou haſt, and procure the increaſe of euill, which thou doeſt diſlike.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14154:53"/>
               <p>Ninthly, in thy zeale for Religion againſt corruptions; let the Booke of God well vnderſtood be thy warrant, and in thy hatred againſt wrongs in the Common-wealth, let the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Law and the equitie thereof mooue thee to ſpeake: this is Religion, this is reaſon. Leſt begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of an ignorant vncertaintie, thou mayſt loſe the fruite of thy labours, and be condemned as a buſie medler, and contentious in a needleſſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>Tenthly, refuſe not to obey Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, in any thing wherein there is not to thee manifeſtly knowne a ſinne to be commited againſt God: let fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſies paſſe; be more loath to offend iuſtly a lawfull Magiſtrate, then to pleaſe the humour of any priuate perſon. Where thou canſt not yeeld, there humbly craue pardon: where thou mayeſt not be tolerated, be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with thy croſſes of afflictions, for ſafetie of conſcience, and beare what thou canſt not auoyde, with a patient minde.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14154:54"/>
               <q>
                  <hi>The Kingdome of God is not meate nor drinke, but righteouſneſſe and peace and ioy in the Holy Ghoſt: for whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in theſe things ſerueth Chriſt, hee is acceptable to God, and approoued of men,</hi> 
                  <bibl>Rom. 14. 17. 18.</bibl>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How to auoide ſcrupuloſitie of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and contention in ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king for reformation.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, Omit no euident and certaine commandement impoſed of God. If there bee nothing but probabilitie of ſinning in obeying the precepts of men; ſet not Opinion before Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Let ancient probability of Truth bee preferred before new coniectures of Errour againſt it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Marke and hold a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene theſe things, the equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Law and the execution; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene eſtabliſhed Truth generally, and perſonall errours of ſome; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene ſoundneſſe of Doctrine and erroneous application; betweene
<pb facs="tcp:14154:54"/> ſubſtance and circumſtance, the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and the matter; betweene the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry being of a thing, and the well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof; betweene neceſſitie and conueniencie; betweene a Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement and a Commandement to thee; betweene lawfulneſſe and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diencie; and betweene that which is giuen abſolutely or in ſome reſpect.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Vſe the preſent good which thou mayſt enioy to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, and an experienced good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou doeſt trouble thy ſelfe, to ſeeke for a ſuppoſed better good vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryed, which thou enioyeſt not. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlike not euer things preſent, as men diſcontented commonly doe: prayſe not things paſt fooliſhly, to diſgrace what now is in being: and deſire not a change, hoping for better vainly. Theſe bee euer the humours of men, the diſeaſes in all States breed them; and light occaſions make the vnwiſe and inconſiderate ſoone to expreſſe them.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, Endeuour for things which are of neceſſitie, wiſh alſo the well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:14154:55"/> of the ſame for conueniency: but for this contend not forcibly againſt publike peace; leſt in ſeeking for the <hi>benè,</hi> thou doeſt vtterly loſe the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the neceſſary <hi>eſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixtly, Doe not trouble thy ſelfe eyther to take part with, or to bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that thing, the holding or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying whereof maketh nothing for or againſt Religion, to further ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or damnation.</p>
               <p>Seuenthly, In a common cauſe make one, but out of thy owne iudgement conuinced of the Truth and within the compaſſe of thy cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; and not for companie ſake to make vp a number, or for that thou wilt be doing, becauſe other are ſo; or for affection to the parties, not being certainly perſwaded of the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the action.</p>
               <p>Eighthly, Neuer preſume to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme other, before thou haſt well or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered thy ſelfe: See at home, then looke abroad; redreſſe that which is faultie, and in thy power to amend, before thou doeſt meddle with that
<pb facs="tcp:14154:55"/> which is beyond thy reach. Be not faire in publike, and foule in priuate, hate hypocriſie, and auoide vaine glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How to auoyde Popery, Schiſme, and vncharitable contentions among one another.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, Receiue no opinion in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but what the Word euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doth warrant: beware of appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions out of thine owne wit, but let the Word firſt giue thee ſight, and ſo entertayne it, as thou art enlighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. As thou mayeſt not of policie for feare of trouble, by thy wit get thee diſtinctions, to loſe ſinceritie where the Word is plaine: ſo mayeſt thou not of ſcrupuloſitie, imagine ſin to trouble thy conſcience, and to vexe thee with feare of tranſgreſſion, where there is no Law: the one doth breed Atheiſme, the other is the Mother of Superſtition.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Let thy owne know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ground thy opinions in thee,
<pb facs="tcp:14154:56"/> and not the meere iudgement of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: ſee into the Glaſſe of the Word by thy owne ſight, without other mens Spectacles; and hold what thou iudgeſt truth, only in loue of the Truth: beware of by-reſpects; hold ſo conſtantly the Truth, as one neuer to be remoued; but euery errour, be willing both to ſee, and to be reclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med from; though thou happeneſt to erre by frailtie, yet become not an Hereticke by obſtinacie.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Witneſſe the Truth, for the Truths ſake: informe other lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingly; deſire that they may ſee the Truth, but neuer vrge them beyond their iudgement, neither take it grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly, if thy words doe not preuaile, but waite with patience. Beware of raſh iudgement, neither condemne nor contemne other that are not as thy ſelfe. Thinke not to make thy gifts anothers guide, nor thy meaſure of grace their rule; for to euery man is allotted his portion.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Whomſoeuer thou doeſt ſee to doe amiſſe, iudge it not to bee
<pb facs="tcp:14154:56"/> of wilfulneſſe, but either of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and ſo offer to informe them, or of infirmitie, and ſo pitie them, them, and pray for them. Be charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſo ſhal not his ſinne hurt thee, and much ſhall thy Charitie aduantage thy ſelfe in the end: and adde this withall, Bee ſlow to anger, let neuer another mans diſtempered paſſion bring thee to diſorderlines in affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, Loue not to bee in Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies, it argueth Pride and a ſpirit of contention: but if thou beeſt drawne vnto them and called there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, vndertake the right, and chuſe the Truth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How a man ought to carrie himſelfe in handling of Controuerſies.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, Neuer come to it with a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudicate opinion, but with a mind to find out the truth, &amp; not of conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Take words doubtfull in the better ſenſe, as the cauſe and circumſtances will beare; euident
<pb facs="tcp:14154:57"/> Truth imbrace willingly, manifeſt errours deny plainly, likelihood of falſhood eſchew friendly, likelihood of Truth bend them the beſt way: peruert nothing wilfully, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thy ignorance and error when thou ſeeſt it, and yeeld the victory for the Truth, ſake to an Aduerſary, and ſeeke not to wreſt it from him by wicked Sophiſtry.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Be ſure in anſwering that thou haſt the Authors meaning, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by which, or to which thou doeſt make anſwere. Alledge no teſtimonie raſhly, and eſpecially beware of this euill in quoting Scripture. Wreſting of Scripture is a great abuſe of the Word; and if thou bee in errour, and doeſt by the Scriptures preſume to maintayne it, thou wouldeſt haue the Truth to vphold falſhood, and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly doeſt make the Holy Ghoſt a maintayner of a lye.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Follow the matter ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, auoid idle excurſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, paſſe by weak neſſe, take heed of haſty paſſions, &amp; in defending a cauſe abuſe no mans per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:14154:57"/>
               <head>How a man ought to carry himſelfe in things indifferent, and what to doe inſcrupuloſitie and doubtful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Conſcience.</head>
               <p>IN things indifferent make no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion for conſcience ſake: ſo it bee that neither holineſſe, merit, nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie bee put therein; nor vſed for any part of Gods worſhip, but for decency, order, and edification.</p>
               <p>If thou be in a doubt, and thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, as thou thinkeſt, doth trouble thee about the vſe of a thing indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent.</p>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>Quaere,</hi> Whether this doubt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth ſimply of a tender conſcience from iudgement conuinced; or that it be but a niceneſſe of diſlike, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from a deſire not to bee trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with them, or for that thou haſt not vſed them, or becauſe ſome can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not away with them, or from a godly iealouſie and ſuſpition only, for from hence will ſcruples ariſe: ſo alſo from a continued cuſtome, likewiſe from ignorance and the want of certayne
<pb facs="tcp:14154:58"/> knowledge, and a ſetled perſwaſion of the lawfulneſſe of a thing. If the<note place="margin">Note well.</note> ground be not a iudgement inlighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and conuinced, it is not trouble of conſcience, but a diſlike working diſcontentedneſſe vpon ſome of theſe former grounds, which thou maiſt eaſily remoue by ſetling thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon the Word and ſound reaſon.</p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>Quaere,</hi> Whether this doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ariſeth through thy own default, by looking out reaſons to encreaſe thy diſlike, and neglecting to ſearch for arguments to giue thee ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. If thus thou haſt offended, as many doe, take as great paynes in Gods ſight to reſolue thy ſelfe, as thou haſt done to bring thy ſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to doubting, elſe dealeſt thou but partially.</p>
               <p n="3">III. <hi>Quaere,</hi> If it bee trouble of conſcience indeed, and yet the thing bee not plainely forbidden, nor ſo commanded; why (where a ſpeciall warrant to a particular is wanting) a generall rule, or a generall comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement
<pb facs="tcp:14154:58"/> 
                  <hi>to obey,</hi> may not giue thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. <hi>Quaere,</hi> Why a man ſhould bee more ſcrupulous to ſeeke to haue warrant plainly for euery thing hee doth in Eccleſiaſticall cauſes, euen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout things indifferent, more then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout matters politike in ciuill affaires. Men in theſe things know not the ground nor end of many things, which they doe yeeld vnto vpon a generall command to obey autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, knowing them not to bee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly againſt Gods will: and yet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery particular obedience in ciuill matters, muſt be, firſt, of conſcience: ſecondly, as ſeruing the Lord (ſo muſt euery Seruant his Maſter:) which cannot bee without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and perſwaſion, that wee doe well euen in that particular, which wee obey in; which men vſually for conſcience ſake inquire not into, but doe reſt themſelues with a generall commandement of obeying lawfull authoritie, ſo it be not againſt a plaine co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement of God. What there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:14154:59"/> doth let, but that a man may ſo ſatisfie himſelfe in matters Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall?</p>
               <p>The curious ſearching ſo particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly into euery thing to haue full ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, hath ſo wrought in theſe dayes vpon mens wits to bring di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions, that the more men ſeeke in doubts for reſolution, the further are they from it. Oh dayes full of diſtractions! what counſell ſhall I here take and giue?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How to ſettle a mans conſcience to preuent ſcrupuloſitie, and perplexitie.</head>
               <p n="1">I. KEepe all mayne truths in the Word, which are moſt plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet downe, and are by the Law of nature ingrauen in euery man.</p>
               <p n="2">II. Beleeue euery Collection tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and neceſſarily gathered by an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate conſequence from the Text.</p>
               <p n="3">III. Follow euident examples fit for thee, either as a Chriſtian, or as thy ſpeciall calling requireth.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14154:59"/>
               <p n="4">IV. Auoid that which is plainely forbidden, or followeth neceſſarily by an immediate conſequence.</p>
               <p n="5">V. Entertayne true Antiquitie, and follow the generall practice of the Church of God in all ages, where they haue not erred from the euident Truth of God.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. If thou ſuffer, let it bee for knowne Truth, and againſt knowne wickedneſſe, for which thou haſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples in the Word, or examples of holy Martyrs in ſtorie ſuffering for the ſame, or the like. But beware of farre-fetched conſequents, or for ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering for new deuices, and for things formerly vnto all ages vnknowne, ſeeme they neuer ſo holy and iuſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to man.</p>
               <p>If yet thou doeſt iudge a thing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded a ſinne, and not to be obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for thy helpe herein, conſider,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:14154:60"/>
               <head>How a thing vnlawfully comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, may bee lawfully obeyed.</head>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>QVaere,</hi> Whether that which is wrongfully or ſinfully com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, may not yet neuertheleſſe be without ſinne obeyed; as <hi>Ioab</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed <hi>Dauid</hi> in numbring the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Then be not thou to blame, but doe what thou oughteſt, albeit o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers doe what they ſhould not.</p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>Quaere,</hi> How thou doſt rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon it euill: if ſimply, then finde a prohibition; elſe, Where no Law is, there is no tranſgreſſion: if acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally, that is in the abuſe that may be remoued; or in reſpect of thy igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the lawfulneſſe, making thee to doubt, and ſo fearing to offend, vſe all diligence for reſolution. And if it bee not a knowne ſinne to thee certainely, but only by probabilities.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quaere,</hi> Whether probabilities of ſinning may giue thee a ſufficient diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge for not obeying a plaine Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, and to neglect neceſſary dueties
<pb facs="tcp:14154:60"/> otherwiſe, both to God and Man.</p>
               <p>If yet thou doeſt thinke thou ſhalt not doe well (albeit the Goſpell may be freely preached thereby) to yeeld ſo much to the euill diſpoſition (ſo ſuppoſed) of men, thinke how Saint <hi>Paul</hi> valued the libertie of preaching the Goſpell; who ſince the Aſcenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt, after that the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall Law was aboliſhed, when hee had preached againſt it, and againſt Circumciſion; yet did checke him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe publikely, and with a place of Scripture, for ſpeaking as hee did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Simonicall, a falſe (in reſpect of his entrance) a perſecuting and murdering high Prieſt: hee obſerued legall Rites, he circumciſed <hi>Timothy,</hi> and did not finde fault with things not altogether to bee approued, ſo long as they were not made a part of Gods worſhip; and all this hee did to procure free libertie to preach the Goſpell.</p>
               <p>And for yeelding ſomewhat to mens euill diſpoſitions, I ſay but thus:</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14154:61"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quaere,</hi> How it could ſtand with <hi>Moſes</hi> faithfulneſſe to grant a bill of diuorcement (contrarie to the Law of marriage, contrarie to the firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution from the beginning) for the very hardneſſe of the peoples hearts, and to preuent a greater miſchiefe?</p>
               <p>If this haply trouble thee (in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what thou mayeſt and oughteſt) that thou ſhalt offend many whom thou wouldſt not offend, then co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How we ought to carry our ſelues in offences taken.</head>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>QVaere,</hi> Whether it bee an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence iuſtly giuen by thee, or taken without iuſt reaſon of them; thou not offending, and they diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, the fault is their owne, and thou art not chargeable therewith.</p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>Quaere,</hi> Whether they be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended in reſpect of what themſelues know, or but lead by affection, diſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king from other mens diſlike? Intreat the former to let thee abound for ſuch things in thine owne ſenſe, and
<pb facs="tcp:14154:61"/> ſhew them that herein thou mayeſt brotherly diſagree: for the later, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme his iudgement, if he will yeeld to reaſon, if not, then,</p>
               <p n="3">III. <hi>Quaere,</hi> Whether thou art bound to nouriſh vp ſuch a one in his folly, and to reſpect his partiall affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, being more carryed away with an ouerweening of ſome mens per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, then any thing at all with the right vnderſtanding of the cauſe? If they be men of iudgement, and will contend with thee, bee not troubled with what wit can inuent to ſay, but what is truly ſpoken from the Word, not by farre Concluſions, but by a neare conſequence, and plaine eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of holy Writ. If thou canſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere the ſubſtance of that which is obiected, let their vaine conceits or ſubtilties paſſe; neither thinke that thou art ouercome, or art bound to yeeld vnto them, as one conuinced in iudgement, becauſe thou canſt not ſee euery deceiueable reply, to giue thereto an vnanſwerable reaſon to take it away. If ignorance make a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiction,
<pb facs="tcp:14154:62"/> and ſophiſtrie be the meanes, then ſhould men be eaſily carryed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with euery winde of doctrine. There is no Heretique but hath his arguments, nor any Sect but hath conceited reaſons, and Satan by his ſophiſtrie helpeth both, the more to beguile others, and euen ſo to deceiue their owne ſelues.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. <hi>Quaere,</hi> What authoritie may doe in things externall for outward rule in the circumſtances of things; and then, Whether Authoritie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding doth not take away the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, which might otherwiſe bee gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in a voluntarie act?</p>
               <p n="5">V. <hi>Quaere,</hi> Whether a man ſhould ſtand more vpon auoiding diſlikes in priuate perſons, then offence to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like authoritie? Whether this be not an humouring of men, to encreaſe diſcontentedneſſe, rather then to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour to preſerue (wherein thou mayeſt) the publike peace and well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of a Chriſtian State; or, Whether it were not better to croſſe ſome mens affections without ſinne to God, then
<pb facs="tcp:14154:62"/> that otherwiſe thou ſhouldeſt ſtay the paſſage of the Goſpell, neglect moſt certayne duties, let people periſh, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen a gap to the enemie, loſe thy li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, &amp; no whit better the Church? It were better, wherein thou lawfully mayeſt, after the Apoſtles practice, that thou diddeſt become all things to all men to winne but ſome.</p>
               <p>Doeſt thou not behold the times? wee haue among vs the Pſeudo-Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, are they not craftie Foxes? diuiſion they ſeeke to hold on foote; they know, a Kingdome diuided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it ſelfe, cannot ſtand. By vnion they ſtrengthen themſelues, by diſ-v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion we grow weake. If we ſupport one another in loue, their enemitie can doe vs no harme. They are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, our innocency is not enough, but we had need to be as wiſe as Serpents; and let vs labour to be of one mind, that we may ioyntly turne our forces againſt them.</p>
               <p>Therefore let vs all, as the Apoſtle exhorteth, ſtudie to be quiet, and to follow thoſe things which concerne
<pb facs="tcp:14154:63"/> our peace with God, within our ſelues, and one with another. And to attayne to this: let vs keepe patience within vs, and bee charitable abroad towards others. Let vs attempt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing raſhly, but firſt know things as they be rightly. We may be, yea wee muſt be zealous, yet in ſound iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without diſtempered paſſion; and not without compaſſion to the tranſgreſſor. In doing any thing (that our courſe may bee good and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) let vs make euer the Word our warrant; the circuit of our calling our bounds and limits; the Spirit of God our Director; our conſcience our Comforter, godly wiſe our Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors; the glorie of God our end; truth and honeſtie the matter for which we contend; the Enemies watchings caueats to vs, to preuent miſcarriage, and to cauſe vs to walk more warily, and all our life to be ſuch as may wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe our readineſſe for death, hauing euer a holy remembrance of our end, and wee ſhall neuer doe amiſſe: Euen ſo, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:14154:63"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
